<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A testimony unto the truth, and a warning unto the world in general, but more particularly to the inhabitants of Enoder parish in Cornwall by ... Richard Samble.</title>
            <author>Samble, Richard, 1644-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 115 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61344</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S531</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23481</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12069035</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12069035</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53475</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61344)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53475)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 577:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A testimony unto the truth, and a warning unto the world in general, but more particularly to the inhabitants of Enoder parish in Cornwall by ... Richard Samble.</title>
                  <author>Samble, Richard, 1644-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 9-55 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n].,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53475:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53475:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TESTIMONY Unto the TRUTH, AND A Warning unto the World IN GENERAL, But more particularly to the Inhabitants of Enoder pariſh in Cornwall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By one whom God hath called out to bear witneſs of the Truth, as it is in Jeſus, called by the Name of</hi> RICHARD SAMBLE.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1676.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:53475:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53475:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>THou art deſired to be conſiderate when thou read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est this following Book, and to be very ponderous in thy Mind, as touching the things therein contained, that thy Underſtanding may be opened by the inviſible God, who giveth unto us</hi> Life, Breath <hi>and</hi> Being; <hi>and alſo, that thou wouldſt lay to Heart this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Thing,</hi> How that Almighty God hath riſen in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ages of the World, in his Judgments and Fury, to ſtain the Glory of all Fleſh, and to ſet up Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs in the Earth, and hath cauſed his Truth to ſpring and flouriſh amongſt his People, under every Diſpenſation, until they departed from the Lord, and ſerved other Gods, and followed their own Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and then Darkneſs came over them, and ſo their Hearts were hardened from his Fear, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.29, 30. <hi>And this thou art alſo to conſider,</hi> That Sin hath been the very Cauſe of Man's Deſtruction from Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration to Generation, and therefore if thou dye in thy Sins, thou art like to have no part amongſt the Living in the Kingdom of Chriſt; but the ſame will be thy Portion that hath been the portion of the
<pb facs="tcp:53475:3"/>Wicked in all Ages, which is perpetual Sorrow, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs and Anguiſh for evermore. <hi>And this conſider alſo,</hi> That whatever thou doſt profeſs, or what Shew of Religion ſoever thou mayeſt make, whilſt thy ſins remain, I am to tell thee, and that in the Name of Chriſt Jeſus, Thou art not accepted of God, but all thy Prayers are an Abomination to the Lord, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 8.17, 18. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.15. becauſe thou art in the Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in that which the pure God of Glory hateth, and upon which he will pour out his Fury and Indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for evermore; and if thou art one that lives in Pleaſure, &amp; thy daily Satisfaction is in following theſe Evil Devices, that are very common amongſt men in this Generation, to wit, Drunkenneſs, Swearing, Lying, or other Prophane Practices, and that which is called Paſtime, or ſporting thy ſelf amongſt ſuch as count it Pleaſure to Riot in the day time, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.5, 6. know this, that all theſe things will be a Hindrance to thy eternal Well-fare; for ſuch as do ſuch things, cannot inherit the Kingdom of God, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19, 20, 21. <hi>And alſo thou art to conſider,</hi> That there hath been a Night of groſs Darkneſs over the Hearts of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men, ſince the Apoſtles dayes; and that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Grace, which was common in that Generation, people have loſt in the Night, and are become dry and barren, as a Deſert or Wilderneſs, as relating to Matters of Spiritual Concerns, wherein conſiſts the Stability of their Souls Peace with God. <hi>And this alſo I am to tell thee,</hi> That God, who is unchangeable, and immortal, hath revealed his bleſſed Truth again, and the Goſpel of his bleſſed Kingdom is now prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb facs="tcp:53475:3"/>to the Nations; and if ever thou comeſt to God's Kingdom, thou muſt come to know him that is the Everlaſting Teacher (to wit) Chriſt Jeſus, and him to know in thy own Particular, who is the Man of God's Right Hand, a quickening Spirit the Lord from Heaven, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.45. and ſo thou wilt come out of thy loſt Condition, wherein thou art in the Fall, in the firſt Man <hi>Adam,</hi> into the Life of Holineſs and Righteouſneſs, into the Reſtoration by Chriſt Jeſus, the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> the Heavenly Man. <hi>And this know alſo,</hi> That thou canſt not come to him by any other way, but as thou comeſt into Self denyal, and belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt in thy Heart the Record that God hath given of his Son, which is the true Light, that ſhines within thee, and lets thee ſee thy Sins. <hi>And farther,</hi> That as ſin hath been the very Cauſe of Man's Separation from the Lord; yet when thou ſhalt return again, and come to know a Godly Sorrow in the Secret of thy Heart, and when thou ſhalt feel in thy ſelf a Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and a Broken-heartedneſs before the inviſible God, who ſees in ſecret, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.6. he will grant thee Repentance unto Life; and he will return unto thee in his Everlaſting Mercies, and blot out thy ſins out of his Remembrance. <hi>And this alſo I am to tell thee, in the Fear of God, and in his Name,</hi> That as the Lord hath appeared in dayes paſt, and in Generations that are gone, in his Indignation, and hath ſmitten many Nations and Peoples in his Wrath, ſometimes overturning the World by Water, and ſometimes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying Cities and Peoples by Fire and Brimſtone from Heaven, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.29. <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.24, 25. and again by
<pb facs="tcp:53475:4"/>Plagues &amp; Peſtilence, and at certain Seaſons the Lord God (becauſe of the Abominations of the Children of Men) hath viſited them in his Wrath and hot Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, and greatly afflicted them; and the End of the Lord hath been, that ſuch as remain upon the Earth might fear before him, and dread his great Name, who is Mighty, and none can eſcape him: <hi>And people in theſe laſt dayes and times have greatly grieved the Lord, and therefore except they Repent, his Fury will he pour forth upon them, until that which is in his Heart be accompliſhed, and they ſhall not eſcape his heavy Hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſo Reader, whoever thou art, that reads theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Lines, the Deſire of my Soul is, that thou mayeſt be impartial concerning me, and conclude in thy Mind, that its written in tender Love to thy Soul, and ſo thou wilt ſee my honeſt Intent, who am a Lover of Truth and Righteouſneſs, deſiring thy Eternal Well-fare when this Time and Day of thine is at an End. I reſt</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Friend and Well-Wiſher, RICHARD SAMBLE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:53475:4"/>
            <head>A TESTIMONY UNTO THE TRUTH, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IN the deep Conſideration of the States and Conditions of the Sons and Daughters of men in the Fall, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how the World lies in the Extremity of Wickedneſs, being overcome by the Old Serpent, called the <hi>Devil</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> who hath tyed and bound them with his Chains of Sin (who is the Author of all Sin) I am drawn in Spirit to warn them to Repentance, and to declare to the World the Way that the Lord God of Heaven and Earth hath ordained, which is Chriſt Jeſus, who is Everlaſting, and <hi>was with the Father before the World began,</hi> John 17.5. <hi>who is the Way, the Truth and the Life,</hi> John 14.6. by whom my Soul hath been redeemed, and who raiſed me up out of Sin; and therefore, having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained Mercy through the Love of God in Chriſt Jeſus, whom he hath ſent a Light into the World, and I having known in meaſure the Judgments of the Lord, and the Terrors of the Almighty becauſe of my Tranſgreſſions, therefore cannot but perſwade men to turn from Ungodlineſs, even all people that lie in Wickedneſs, knowing aſſuredly, that <hi>all People ſhall be called to an Account before the Tribunal Seat of Chriſt, there to give an Account for the Deeds done in the Body,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.10. <hi>and ſuch as have done well, ſhall receive a Crown of Life and Peace with God forever; and they that have done Evil, ſhall go into Everlaſting Puniſhment,</hi> Mat. 25.46. And therefore, as you have been Tranſgreſſors againſt God, and Strangers to the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53475:5"/>Life of Holineſs, it is upon my Spirit from the Lord God to warn you ſpeedily, to turn every one from the Evil of your Wayes, that out of Darkneſs you all may come, and out of Ignorance and Blindneſs, unto Chriſt Jeſus, the true Way, that you may have Life, who ſaid, <hi>I am come that you may have Life, and that you may have it more abundantly,</hi> John 10.10. And therefore turn unto him in your Hearts, whoſe Spiritual Appearance is inwardly, whom God hath ſent a Light into the World, <hi>John</hi> 1.9. Now that all may come unto him, and believe in your Hearts the Lord Jeſus, and be ſaved; for people have been in a great Miſtake concerning the Faith that ſaves and overcomes the World; for the true <hi>Faith is the Gift of God,</hi> Epheſ. 2.8. ariſing from the <hi>Word of Faith nigh in the Heart, Rom.</hi> 10.8. which Faith <hi>Chriſt is the Author of, and the Finiſher alſo,</hi> Heb. 12.2. and <hi>without this Faith you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pleaſe God,</hi> Hebr. 11.6. And ſo all People. read your States and Condition in the Light of Chriſt within you, which ſhews unto you what you are, and declares unto you your Thoughts, this is the Record which God hath given of his Son in the Earth, which is Eternal Life, and this Life is in his Son, <hi>John</hi> 5.11. this reproves you in ſecret for ſin; this is the Holy Spirit of Promiſe that was to come, whom the Prophets pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of in the dayes of old, whom God hath given for a Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and a Commander of the People, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.4. the <hi>Gentiles Light</hi> and <hi>Iſrael's Glory,</hi> Luke 2.32. and unto him you muſt turn, <hi>who ſtands at the Door of your Hearts and knocks,</hi> Revel. 3.20. who is come to deſtroy Sin in the Fleſh; whoſe living Power was felt in the Hearts of many Thouſands in dayes paſt, after his Reſurrection, in the dayes of the Apoſtles, when he returned to his Glory that he had with the Father before the World was; who deſcended firſt into the loweſt parts of the Earth, and aſcended up far above all Heavens (<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.9, 10.) that he might fill all things, whoſe Glory fills Heaven and Earth; neither is there any Creature that is not manifeſt in his Sight, but <hi>all things are naked and open to the Eye of him with whom we have to do,</hi> Hebr. 4.13. <hi>who dyed for our Sins, and roſe again for our Redemption and Juſtification,</hi> Rom. 4.25.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53475:5"/>who appeared firſt to <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> and made her a Preacher of his Reſurrection, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.10. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.9. and then to his Diſciples, before he aſcended into Heavenly Glory: And when he aſcended up on high, <hi>he led Captivity captive, und gave Gifts unto Men,</hi> Epheſ. 4.8. And though he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to his Diſciples as they ſate at Meat, yet he bad them <hi>wait for the Gift of the Spirit, when he aſecended unto the Father,</hi> Luke 4.49. And ſo they were made Witneſſes of his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, that he roſe out of the Grave, and not only ſo, but that he was in Heavenly Glory, who came again, as he had foretold his Diſciples, who ſaid, <hi>Ye have heard how I ſaid, I go away, and come again unto you,</hi> &amp;c. John 14.28. And as the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>he was offered up once for all, and to every one that looks for him, will he appear the ſecond time without Sin unto Salvation;</hi> and by his ſpiritual Appearance were many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands gathered, and many were made able Miniſters of the New Teſtament, not of the Letter, but of the Spirit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. And this Spirit of Grace taught them to deny all Ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and worldly Luſts, and to live ſoberly and righteouſly in this preſent World, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.12. And this Grace of God that bringeth Salvation, hath appeared unto all men, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11. even to <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile;</hi> the Grace of God, the pure Spirit of Chriſt, the Light of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> unto which Light the Apoſtles were ſent to turn the Heathen, that had no wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Law in thoſe Days; and from the Power of Satan unto God, <hi>Acts</hi> 28.8. Thus the Lord ſtretched forth his Everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Arm of Strength and Power in thoſe Days, that People might be gathered unto him, and raiſed up by Chriſt Jeſus, out of Death and ſpiritual Bondage; and thoſe Preachers of the Glorious Goſpel of God's Kingdom, travailed chearfully in the Lord's Work, and preached freely, as they had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved freely, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.8. declaring both to <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> that God hath raiſed his Son from the dead. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.24, 25. and that the Day of Joy and Glad tidings was come, wherein Deliverance from the wicked one was to be known, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption from dead Works to ſerve the living God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. who waited for the Son from Heaven (mark that) you
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53475:6"/>that are Preachers in this Nation. The Apoſtles did not come to People with Enticing Words of Man's Wiſdom, but directed them to the Light that was revealed from Heaven (to wit) the Son of God the Light of the World, <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4. <hi>John</hi> 1.9. and if you turn not People to the Son of God the Light of the World, to wait for him inwardly, then ye are blinded and are in Darkneſs and preach another Goſpel then Chriſt jeſus, whom the Apoſtles did preach, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8. for Chriſt Jeſusſaid, <hi>Seek not the Kingdom in Obſervations; for behold, the Kingdom of Heaven is within you,</hi> Luke 17.21. And <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romans</hi> ſaith, <hi>That which may be known of God, is manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in them; for God hath ſhewed it unto them,</hi> Rom. 1.19. And the true Goſpel is the Power of God, wherein the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of God is revealed from Faith to Faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16, 17. and the Light of this Glorious Goſpel ſhines within, and if this glorious Goſpel be hid, it is to them that are loſt, in whom the God of this World hath blinded the Minds of them that believe not, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3, 4. And you that have not this Goſpel take heed how you preach, leſt you be found falſe Witneſſes, runnning before the true Guide Chriſt Jeſus, and profeſſing God and Chriſt, and yet dead in Sin, all ſuch Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Hearers that are not come to the Goſpel within, to the Word of Eternal Life in their Hearts, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.12. are out of the Truth, in the Fall, and ſo abiding in Death; for he that hath not the Son (who is the Truth) hath not Life; for this living Word within, was the Foundation of the Holy Prophets and Apoſtles, by which they were made alive; and this did divide between the good &amp; bad, which Word is quick and powerful, and ſearcheth the Heart, and trieth the Reins, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.23. And it is the ſame to this Day as ever it was, yea, it lives and abides for ever, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. And the Primitive C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riſtians who were true Believers, their Faith did ariſe from this living Word, which came down from Heaven; And Wo be to ſuch as turn away from him that ſpeaks from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.25. which is ſent forth from God (to deſtroy the Works of the Devil) 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.8. Chriſt Jeſus the Seed Immortal and Incorruptible, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. that bruiſeth the Head
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53475:6"/>of the Serpent, and by this Seed they were redeemed (in the Days of the Apoſtles) and brought forth and born of it, not of corruptible Seed, but of incorruptible; and this Seed muſt be witneſſed within, as in the Days of Old, to raiſe up Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind out of the Fall inwardly, and to quicken to God by his Spirit that dwelleth in you, ſaid the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11. And this is the true Shepherd that laid down his Life for the Sheep, <hi>John</hi> 10.11. that gathers his Sheep from the Barren Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, where they have been ſcattered in the cloudy dark Day, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.12. and brings out of the Wilderneſs and Solitary Ways, into a ſure Dwelling, and a quiet Reſting Place, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32.18. And this true Biſhop of the Soul was known ſavingly in the primitive times, by all thoſe that did return unto him, as the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>Ye were as Sheep going aſtray, but are now returned to the Shepherd and Biſhop of your Souls,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.25. And ſo by the Operation of his Spirit inwardly, People came to the Knowledge of God and Chriſt Jeſus, whom God ſent forth to ſave the World; and this is Life Eternal, as our Lord ſaid in the Days of his Fleſh, <hi>to know thee the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent,</hi> John 17 3. And there is not another Way to Salvation, but as People come to know Chriſt revealed in them, as the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>Examine your ſelves, prove you own ſelves, what, know you not how that Chriſt Jeſus is in you except you be Reprobates?</hi> 2 Cor. 13 5. but in thoſe Days this pure Way of Life was hid from the wiſe and prudent, and revealed to Babes and Sucklings (mark) ſuch as were born again, regenerated and walked in the Way of Regeneration, thoſe only knew the Myſteries of God's Kingdom; for it was revealed unto them by the Spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.10. But the wiſe Men who were outſide Profeſſors (yet Rebellious and Stiff necked, and a Gainſaying People) unto whom God ſtretched forth his Hand all the Day long, but they would not obey him, nor hearken to his Voice, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.21. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.51. Theſe knew not Chriſt in the Myſtery, but cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified him, though they were I rofeſſors and had a Zeal for the Traditions of their Fore-Fathers, yet I ſay the Workings of God's Spirit was a ſtrange Thing unto them, for ſaid the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53475:7"/>
               <hi>We preach Chriſt in a Myſtery, which none of the Princes of this World knew; for if they had known him, they would not have crucified the Lord of Life</hi> 1 Cor. 2.7, 8. And thoſe holy Apoſtles and Servants of Chriſt, who preacht by the Spirit, even by the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.12. they were hated, and perſecuted, and ſet at nought, and eſteemed as a Fooliſh and Ignorant People, as the off-ſcouring of all things, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13. And ſaid the Apoſtle, <hi>God hath made fooliſh the Wiſdom of this World. When the World by Wiſdom knew not God, it pleaſed God by the Fooliſhneſs of Preaching to ſave them that believe,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 20.21. So thoſe that were Enemies to God, and to the Appearance of his Son; they caſt him (that is the true Heir) out of the Vin yard, and ſlew him, that the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance might be theirs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.38, 39. So read this ye pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Chriſtians, who are in the Rebellion againſt Chriſt's Appearance, who is now appeared in Spirit in theſe laſt Days, Glory to the Name of the Lord forever. And is not this it that you rebel againſt, even his Appearance in your Hearts, that breaks your Peace in the Tranſgreſſion, and brings forth your Deeds which you have wickedly wrought in ſecret, to your Remembrance? And do you not love Darkneſs rather then Light becauſe your Deeds are evil, <hi>John</hi> 3.19. And are you not in the ſame Tranſgreſſion with thoſe <hi>Jews</hi> who hated his Appearance in the Fleſh? and are turned from Jeſus Chriſt in your Hearts, and conſulting together againſt him (who is the Light &amp; Life of Men) how you may betray and overcome this true Principle of Eternal Life in your ſelves &amp; others, that you may ſet up your ſelves, and live in your Pride and Loſtineſs, and all manner of Wickedneſs; and ſo in much Wantonneſs you paſs and ſpend away your precious time, in Rioting and Drunkenneſs, in Chambering and Wantonneſs which is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, and will be eternally puniſhed, <hi>James</hi> 5.5, 6. And ſo you live above the Croſs of Chriſt Jeſus, the Power of God in your own Hearts, which Croſs ſaid the Apoſtle, <hi>Cruciſies the World unto me, and me unto the World:</hi> And ſo you are found Enemies to God, reſiſting the holy Ghoſt, as they that caſt him out in Days paſt, and would not believe that it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53475:7"/>was he: And ſaid Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>If ye believe not that I am he, you ſhall dye in your Sins,</hi> John 8.24. Acts 7.51. <hi>Ye ſhall ſeek me, but ſhall not find me; and whither I go, thither ye cannot come.</hi> So all People, believe that it is he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves you in ſecret, and obey him in your Hearts, leſt you dye in your Sins, &amp;c. for it is ſurely the ſame true Witneſs that in old time teſtified of the World, <hi>that the Works thereof are Evil,</hi> John 7.7. which is a ſure Witneſs, that doth not alter, but is Unchangeable, <hi>with whom there is no Variableneſs, James</hi> 1.17. but if you rebel againſt him, who is the great Power of God, Chriſt Jeſus, WO will be unto you for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <p>Therefore I warn you in God's holy Fear, and in the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his Spirit, That you rebel no longer againſt God; for if ye continue in the Rebellion againſt him, Time will not bring End to your Miſery, but you will go into Everlaſting Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo take heed to your wayes, leſt ye be found with <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> betraying his Maſter; for <hi>Judas</hi> was a Profeſſor of Chriſt, and yet apoſtatized: So ye profeſſing <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> take heed leſt ye be found in the Treachery, dealing deceitfully againſt the Light of Chriſt Jeſus in your Hearts, profeſſing him with your Mouthes, and denying him in your Hearts, who is the Spirit of Truth, that <hi>reproves the World of Sin, Righteouſneſs and of Judgment,</hi> Joh. 16.8. And therefore examine your ſelves, and try whether ye be in the true Faith; for there is but One Lord, One Faith and One Baptiſm, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.5. which is the Baptiſm of the Holy Ghoſt, the pure Spirit of Life, <hi>which baptizeth into one Body,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.13. (And ſo all other Faiths and Baptiſms will come to an End) and this brings into true Love and Unity one with another: And this true Faith works by Love, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6. But in this dark Night of Apoſtacy, the World, that hath retained a Form of Godlineſs in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide Profeſſion of Chriſt hath been ſetting up Faiths and Forms of Worſhip, from the true Faith, and true Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, which is in the Spirit, <hi>John</hi> 4.23. and out of the Power and Life (in the dark) out of the Light, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53475:8"/>the Fellowſhip of the Saints ſtood in the dayes of old, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.7. And this Faith, that's of man's making and ſetting forth works not by Love, neither brings people into Unity and a holy Fellowſhip one with another; but people are brought under by Conſtraint, and by outward Force; and ſuch as are in their Way zealous for their Worſhip, run into Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, and ſo the Ground is not good, the Heart is not changed, but the old Man of Sin remains; and this is far from the true Faith, that works by Love: and many times people, whoſe Hearts God hath touched, are compelled to go to ſuch Worſhips againſt that which hath in ſome meaſure given them to ſee the Inſufficiency of thoſe Worſhips and Faiths that ſtand not in God's Power.</p>
            <p>And ſo people, you that are in any meaſure made tender in your Conſciences, and are breathing inwardly for Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance (that you may witneſs Redemption to your Souls) and know not the true Way, and are many times afflicted inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and accept not Faith to believe in yout Hearts on the Lord Jeſus, Wait you in the Senſe of that which begets the Brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things, and pens your Hearts for the Deſire to ſpring forth, that deſires after the Lord, and that will let you ſee the Way more and more, yea, the inviſible Way of God, Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, <hi>who is the Way, the Truth and the Life,</hi> John 14.6. and then you will have Faith to believe that God will bring you forth out of the Falſe Wayes of this World, into Peace with himſelf, and into Covenant with him, and ſo your Hearts will be changed, and you will come to witneſs inwardly the Law of the Spirit of Life written in your Hearts, and ſo then you will have no need to wander abroad, to ſeek Chriſt Jeſus in the dark wayes of this World; but you will all know the VVay of his Appearance in your ſelves, and ſo <hi>you will be his People, and he will be your God,</hi> Hebr. 8.10. And this is the ſame Truth that was in the dayes of the Apoſtles, Chriſt, the true Foundation, that upheld all the true <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in the former dayes, who were the true Church, <hi>in Covenant with God, joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto the Lord, and ſo were Heirs of God's Kingdom, yea,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53475:8"/>joynt Heirs with Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 8.17. Epheſ. 2.20. and this was a <hi>true Church, that was in God, and in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> 1 Theſ. 1.1. not an outſide Profeſſion only, but an inward Poſſeſſion, a people that were <hi>riſen with Chriſt, ſeeking the things that are above, where Chriſt ſitteth at the Right Hand of God,</hi> Colloſſ. 3.1. So they had Heavenly Riches and Treaſure, laid up in Heaven, that faileth not: And this true Church was the Houſe of God, not an Outward Houſe, builded with men's Hands, but a Spiritual Houſe, a People made alive to God, by Chriſt Jeſus, and ſo they were <hi>the Workmanſhip of God, Epheſ.</hi> 2.10. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. But ſince the Apoſtacy came in, and people having gone a whoring from the Lord, they have not known this Myſtery; but have been building High Places, and calling them <hi>Churches,</hi> and <hi>God's Houſe,</hi> contrary to the Scriptures; and ſo People have loſt the true Senſe and ſaving Knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus, though they have the Letter of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>criptures, which tells us plainly, that <hi>the Bodies of the true</hi> Chriſtians <hi>are God's Temples and his Houſe,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.15, 19. And his Church is of his building, and of his raiſing up, who is the ſure VVorkman, even Jeſus Chriſt, that makes alive, and brings up Mankind unto God, out of the Fall; and of this Church he was and is the Head, who is worthy of more Honour then the Houſe, which is his <hi>Church, the Ground and Pillar of Truth,</hi> 1 Tim. 3.15. So Chriſt Jeſus was in his Houſe, in his Church, over which he ruled and was the Head; and he is in his Church to this day, and is the true Head, the true Guide and Leader of his People, that are quickned by him, and brought forth to Praiſe him, with one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ongue and one Morth even as one Body And ſo all people, come to know Chriſt in you, as they that we read of in the Scriptures, <hi>Coll</hi> 26.27. for this is a Time wherein he is to be ſound, if you ſeek to him berimes, and not ſleight the Day of your Viſitation; for the Viſitation of the Almighty is come, and he hath cauſed the Day pring from on Pigh to viſit us, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.78, 79. in which the Lord will bring to paſs that which hath been of old in his Determination (viz) <hi>to ſet up Righteouſneſs in the Earth;</hi> and this Day ſhall never have an End; it the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53475:9"/>laſting Diſpenſation, <hi>that ſhall never more be vailed,</hi> Prov. 14.6. and bleſſed are all that come to the Knowledge of it; and in the firſt Breakings forth of it in the dayes of the Apoſtles, many Thouſands were gathered to God; and that which was the Cauſe of its being vailed from man's Underſtanding was, becauſe of the Unfaithfulneſs of ſuch as did profeſs the Truth, whoſe Candleſtick at laſt was removed out of its place, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.5. and Darkneſs came over them, who retained a Form of Godlineſs, and loſt the Power thereof, and theſe were the firſt that rebelled againſt the Spirit of Chriſt in the dayes of the Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.51. and ſo the Devil got the Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their Hearts, and ſate in the Temple of God, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf that he is God, 2 <hi>Theſſ</hi> 2.4. Therefore, oh ye profeſſing <hi>Chriſtians!</hi> ſearch your ſelves, let not the Devil rule in your Hearts, for all Unrighteouſneſs is begotten in the Heart by the Devil, who is the Author of all Sin in the Heart, before it be committed; but turn to the Light of Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that convinceth your Conſciences, and ſhews you the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gettings of that falſe ſpirit, and ſo you will know Deliverance from the ſubtil Serpent, the Enemy of all Mankind: for it is high time to look about you, and conſider whoſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants you are, and to whom you yield your ſelves Servants to obey, and whoſe Work you are doing, whether ye are obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt Jeſus in the Spirit of Truth, that leads out of the World's Wayes, Faſhions and Cuſtoms, into all Truth (<hi>John</hi> 14, 16, 17, 20,) and Righteouſnes, that ye may know ye are his Sheep; for, <hi>My Sheep,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>hear my Voice,</hi> (John 10.11, 14.) <hi>and I lead them out, and they follow me, and ill give unto them Eternal Life,</hi> John 10.28. Or whether you are obeying the Devil, which is the Spirit of Error, which leads your Minds into the Wickedneſs which is in the World, out from God and Chriſt Jeſus the true Light, into Darkneſs and Death, and ſo you are under the Bondage of Corruption, polluted with all manner of Uncleanneſs, and ſo in the Way to Everlaſting Deſtruction, and as the Ground that bringeth forth Bryers and Thorns, which is nigh unto Curſing, whoſe End is to be burned; for <hi>his Servants you are to whom you yield
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53475:9"/>your ſelves to obey, whether of Sin unto Death, or of Obedience unto Righteouſneſs,</hi> Rom. 6.16. for its not ſufficient to ſay with your Mouthes and your Lips, <hi>We believe in God and Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> while ye abide in the Tranſgreſſion, and your Hearts far from him; and <hi>that he dyed without the Gates of</hi> Jeruſalem, and ye ſtill live in the Nature of the Wicked One; this is the ſame as they in old time, who retained a Form of Godlineſs, and denyed the Power thereof, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. who were Falſe Apoſtles, Deceitful Workers, transforming themſelves into the Apoſtles of Chriſt, <hi>and its no Marvel,</hi> ſaid the Apoſtle, <hi>for Satan himſelf is transformed into an Argel of Light, and it's no great thing if his Miniſters alſo be transformed as the Miniſters of Righteouſneſs, whoſe End ſhall be according to their Works,</hi> 2 Cor. 11.13, 14, 15. And this was the great Deceit that entered into the Church, and began in the Days of the Apoſtles, when that falſe Spirit of Antichriſt ſeduced thoſe that were called Chriſtians, I ſay ſuch as were deceitful Profeſſors of Chriſt Jeſus in that Day, who turned aſide after filthy Lucre into <hi>Balaam</hi>'s VVay, and ſo loved this preſent VVorld, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.15. and theſe denyed the Immediate working of the Spirit of Chriſt, and ſo became Enemies to God, and unto the Croſs of Chriſt, <hi>whoſe God is their Belly, whoſe Glory is their Shame, who mind earthly things,</hi> ſaid the Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19. and ſaid <hi>Jude, Beloved you have heard before of the Apoſtles of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, how that there ſhould Mockers come in the laſt time, walking after their own ungodly Luſts, theſe be they</hi> ſaid he, <hi>who ſeparate themſelves,</hi> Jude 18, 19. <hi>ſenſual not having the Spirit;</hi> and theſe were they that denyed the only Lord God, and our Lord jeſus Chriſt ſavingly, under the Diſpenſation of the Goſpel, who rebelled againſt the Spirit and Power of God in their Hearts; and theſe were <hi>corrupted &amp; deceitful treacherous, Heady, High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded, Lovers of Pleaſure more then Lovers of God</hi> 2 Tim. 3.3, 4. And thus the Devil (by his Inſinnuations) brought in the Apoſtacy, and led People into the Rebellion againſt the Light and Spirit of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo People have been bewildred, and greatly deſolated ſince the Days of the Holy Apoſtles, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.6. and VVanderers from Hill to Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53475:10"/>even from one dry Profeſſion to another, in the Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Tranſgreſſion, and ſo Ignorance hath abounded in the Kingdoms of men, and the general Doctrine hath Been denying the work of the Spirit of Chriſt within, and the Light not to be the Way, and ſo People are b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inded from time to time, and following the Spirit &amp; Power of Darkneſs, who leads from God and Chriſt Jeſus who is Light and Life (to the Souls that obey him) into Death and Sorrow, under the We and Indignation of Almighty God. Now conſider ye that are denying the Working of the Spirit of God within you, and ſay, <hi>Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ceaſt.</hi> Oh that you would diligently weigh this thing in the juſt Ballance in your own Hearts! Is not this the denying of Chriſt? for God looks to the Heart, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.17. and not to the outward Appearance; and all that deny the Spirit of Chriſt within, they have broken Covenant with God, and are in Danger of Eternal Death, and ſo go a whoring after other Gods, and other Lovers, as the old apoſtate <hi>Jews,</hi> who turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed aſide into by Paths, and crooked Ways from the Way of Life, whoſe Services, Sacrifices and offerings, New moons and Sabbaths were all an Abomination to the Lord, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.13. And ſo you that deny the work of the Spirit in your Hearts, your Service, Worſhips and Ordinances are not acceptable to the Lord, becauſe Sin remains, the Sting of Death yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken away, you remaining in the Guilt dead in Treſpaſſes and Sins, and ſo the Spirit of the VVicked One keeps the Houſe, &amp; hath the Poſſeſſion in the Heart, who hath no right to reign in the Hearts of the Children of Men, therefore as the wicked Spirit hath reigned, which hath led you into Darkneſs, and poſſeſſed you with a Perſwaſion that Revelation is ceaſt, now examine and try your ſelves that he may be caſt out, and your Hearts cleanſed, and your Souls redeemed, that Chriſt may reign whoſe right it is, and ſo you will come to know the VVorking of God's Holy Spirit, the true Power, Chriſt Jeſus, who is come to deſtroy Sin in the Fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3. to the 11th. and as you yield your ſelves unto him inwardly, ſo the Change of the Mind you will come to witneſs, and your Affections, Deſires and Inclinations will be redeemed out of the Earthly
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53475:10"/>corruptible things, and Vanities of the VVorld, into a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly-mindedneſs; and ſo you will have Treaſure in Heaven with the Lord, being delivered from the Power of Death and Darkneſs, which rules in the Hearts of the Children of Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and ſo you will be true VVitneſſes for God that he hath raiſed up his Son from the dead, who is become a quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Spirit, who works in the Hearts of all that obey him, and theſe are the true Chriſtians this Day, who are redeemed by Chriſt Jeſus to God, out of the Fall, out of the Death, that came by Sin, into the Life, that came by Chriſt Jeſus who ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not, and ſo you will know in your ſelves the Truth and the VVay which is Holy, and no Defilement at all in it, which is the Light and Life of Men, Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>John</hi> 1.4. for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly the Day, is dawned wherein God hath opened the VVay of Truth, which is not another, but the ſame as in old time, which is the VVay of Holineſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.3. &amp; 35.8. And though this ſeems to be a ſtrange thing to preach Chriſt Jeſus in Spirit (this Day) who is the Light of the VVorld, as God hath ſent him forth to enlighten every man that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into the VVorld, <hi>John</hi> 1.4, 9. yet we know to our Souls Comfort and Satisfaction, that he is come, whoſe Power and Dominion ſhall ſway and bear Rule in the Hearts of the Sons and Daughters of Men, until he hath utterly waſted that wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Nature in Man that rebels againſt him, and will not that he ſhould reign, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.27. And though People have rebelled againſt him in this Night of Darkneſs, and the Clouds there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of have ſhaddowed, vailed and darkned the Underſtandings of the Sons of Men, yet that ſhall not make void the Ancient Promiſe of God, who ſaid, <hi>that the Knowledge of his Glory ſhould fill the Earth, as the Waters cover the Sea,</hi> Iſa. 11.9. Hab. 2.14. neither ſhall it fruſtrate the Intention of the Lord, whole Determination hath been and is, <hi>to make an End of Sin, and bring in Everlaſting Righteouſneſs,</hi> Dan. 9.24. though the Enemy of the Souls of Men hath brought in a great and deep Myſtery of iniquity under a Pretence of Religion in theſe latter Ages and Generations of the World, yet it's not that which muſt ſtand in the Earth, being polluted and defiled, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53475:11"/>are ſuch polluted Worſhippers (who are bound with the Chain of Sin) accepted of God, who are placed in the Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of Cruelty: And ſo the wicked One hath been poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Minds, and Hearts of thoſe who wander from God in their Imaginations, that Revelation is ceaſed; but though this Doctrine be preached, as though God would work no more in the Children of Men, I ſay it is not conſiſtent with Truth, but is of the falſe Part in man that wanders from God, and therefore ſhall not hinder the Lord from breaking forth in this his Day, to redeem a People to himſelf for his own Glory, neither doth it hinder, or ſtop the Bleſſings of God unto his People, and redeemed ones, who wait to be ſuſtained by him with the Bread of Life, but the Lord is at work in this his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Day, wherein he hath ſent forth a Saviour, even jeſus who is revealed from Heaven; and your preaching againſt the Work of the Spirit of Chriſt within, will not be ſufficient in the great Day of Account, to ſtop (but rather to haſten) the Eternal Judgment from being executed upon you, who are in the Deceivableneſs of Unrigteouſneſs with them that periſh, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10. Oh that you would lay to Heart theſe things, &amp; repent and live, while your Day laſteth, that you may come forth from all your Abominations, and believe the true Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in your Conſciences that records your Deeds, for which if ye repent not, you will ſuffer in time to come, and ſuch as deny the Work of the Spirit within, are one with them that went out from the Apoſtles Fellowſhip, that ſtood in a rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated State, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.7. who walkt in the Light, and had Fellowſhip with God, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.3. And ſince the firſt turning from God, out of the Heavenly Light, how hath the Devil deceitfully wrought in the Kingdoms of this World? but bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for ever be the Name of our God, the true Light is come, that lets us ſee through the groſs Darkneſs of this Night of Apoſtacy, wherein the Stars that have fallen from Heaven have been wandering in the Night of Darkneſs, having loſt their Habitations, for whom the Blackneſs of Darkneſs is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved forever, <hi>Jude</hi> 13. And therefore you that have loſt the Truth, and are yet in the Death, that came by <hi>Adams</hi> Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53475:11"/>you that have gotten the Name <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and loſt the Power and Life of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> unto you this opens in my Heart to write; if ever you be ſaved, you muſt come to that which was in the Beginning before the Apoſtacy entered, and before they denyed the work of the Spirit, even to the Word that God hath given of his only Son, which is the living Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in you, teſtifying againſt your Evil Deeds; and ſo your Eyes will be opened to ſee the Death that hath reigned over Mankind ſince the Working of the Spirit of Chriſt hath been denyed; and alſo you will ſee the Work that God hath begun, and is doing in this his Day, who hath ſhewed forth his Strength in the Redemption of a little Remnant, who are true Worſhipers, who worſhip the Father in the Spirit &amp; in the Truth, <hi>John</hi> 4.23, 24. but if you hold to the Traditions of your Fathers, who deny Revelation, and ſo have ſet up your Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, not expecting the Spirit to be revealed in you, then I ſay, you cannot be ſaved; for without the Spirit man is dead to God, and Righteouſneſs, and Holineſs; and ſo without Holineſs no man ſhall ſee the Lord, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. and this is the Groſs Darkneſs that is over many this Day, who are ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon their Lees, as <hi>Moab</hi> of old, not being emptied from Veſſel to Veſſel, <hi>Jer.</hi> 48.11. not knowing the Lord's Power in them to change their Hearts, and ſuch have ſet themſelves againſt the Spirit of Truth within, and cry out to People that Revelation is ceaſt, in ſuch a Day as this wherein the Iniquity of many is even come to the full, and wherein God hath affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to Mankind a Day of Viſitation that they may be ſaved. So in a general Senſe, the Wiſe and Learned amongſt men in the Apoſtacy, in their ſeveral Profeſſions, are reſting in ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing beſides the Spirit, and ſo eſteem the Profeſſion without the Spirit, that firſt in the days of old the true Chriſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and obeyed, by which they were brought to profeſs Chriſt Jeſus; and ſo their Profeſſion and Worſhip was not only in a Form, but in the Power and Spirit of God, until the Deceiver entred, and then they retained the Form, and loſt the Power, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3 5. and now through the Diſobedience of Mankind, and rebelling againſt the Power, they have undertook to gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53475:12"/>and reſiſt the Holy Ghoſt, even the Holy Spirit which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the true Leader to God's Kingdom, as did their Fore-Fathers, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.51, 52. Oh that you would return to God! Ye pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing People while you have a Day; for now is a time where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you may find the Lord, if you ſeek him early; for he hath ſaid, <hi>They that ſeek him early ſhall find him,</hi> Iſa. 55.6, 7. And now all ſuch as deny the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt, they are ſeen to be in the Deceit, and in the old corruptible Way, as in the Days of old, in the broad Way that leads to Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.13. where no true Peace is, but men out of God's Counſel, running not being ſent of God, and ſo profit not the People at all, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.32. And now as one whom God hath raiſed up to proclaim his ancient Truth againſt all the Deceit that hath entered into the World in the Night of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for the Sakes of ſuch as have Deſires after the Lord, this is written; for there are many, I do believe, that are amongſt you, whoſe Hearts the inviſible God hath touched by his word which is Eternal, and from the Beginning, that is nigh in your Hearts, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.11, 12, 13, 14. &amp; <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.6, 7, 8. at certain Seaſons, being quick and powerful, ſharper then a two-edged Sword, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. which doth open the Secrets of your Hearts, and declares unto you your Thoughts, ſo that you need not go far away to ſeck a Saviour, but wait for him from Heaven to be revealed within you, as the Apoſtle direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. and then you will find him, who is the true Beloved; for if ever you come to the true Enjoyment of him, you muſt wait for him in his own Way, who is Heavenly, and comes from his Holy Habitation: and you muſt turn from the blind Watch-men, who are in the Night, who have loft the Way of his Appearance, and are turned againſt him, even fighting againſt his Appearance with their filthy Weapons, pleading for ſin, for which Cauſe the Earth mourns, and the Inhabitants thereof (who are redeemed) take up a Lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Conſideration of theſe things. And all you that are thus touched inwardly, and tendred in any meaſure, in the Bowed-dowaneſs of your Souls, ſeeking the Lord that you may be ſaved, oh! go not forth after your Imaginations to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53475:12"/>ſeek him in the Deſert, nor after ſuch as ſay, <hi>Lo here,</hi> or <hi>Le there, Go ye not after them, nor follow them,</hi> Mat. 24.23. but wait, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving your Minds retired in the Manifeſtation of his heavenly Light within you, and then ye will come to a true and certain Knowledge of him; and ſo you will ſee how the Wiſe have Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, &amp; how they are gone back into the old By-Pathes that they were in that could not ſpeak a Word in Seaſon to the Soul that is weary, but ſhut the Kingdom of Heaven againſt men, and hindred ſuch as were entring, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.13. therefore WO was cryed againſt them, which WO ſtands over the Heads of all that are in the Rebellion againſt the Spirit of God to this day: And is it not even ſo? Do not our Wiſe Men and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors ſhut the Kingdom againſt men? Do not they preach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Entrance into Life Eternal, ſaying, <hi>Revelation is ceaſed;</hi> and this ſad Doctrine hath filled the Land with Uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties, and many Thouſands are like to periſh and dye in their Sins through Unbelief, <hi>John</hi> 8.21, 24. Now all you that are out of the Light of Life, in the World of Death and Darkneſs, and are perſwaded, <hi>though you dye in your (Sins and) <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs yet you ſhall be ſaved,</hi> not being freed by Chriſt Jeſus from the Act of Sin here in this Life: Troly this is a falſe Faith and Hope, that will come to an End; for Sin ever was and is the Cauſe of man's Separation from God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.1, 2. and God ſent his Son to deſtroy Sin in the Fleſh, and to be a Propitiation for the Sins of the whole World, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.2. And though People have forſaken the Lord God of Power and Life, yet he hath again viſited with his Ancient Mercies, the Sons of men, to the End they might not periſh, and his Ancient Arm is revealed, that gathers to himſelf; and though the Night hath been long and tedious, wherein the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy of the Soul hath poſſeſſed the Place and Seat in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4. yet now the Lord calls for Repentance, and for all to come unto him out of their Sins, and from under Satan's Power; and whoſoever comes unto him, he will in no wayes caſt out, <hi>John</hi> 6.37. but in this Day, who refuſeth to hearken to his Heavenly Voice, and come not unto him, they will unavoidably periſh for evermore, and their Blood ſhall be
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53475:13"/>upon their own Heads; for there is no way to God's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but as Redemption is witneſſed by Chriſt Jeſus out of the loſt State, and ſo being reſtored to God by Chriſt Jeſus, you come into the Way of Life, where Peace with God is known; and this hath been the Happineſs of People in all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Generations, as they have come up into Obedience, out of the Tranſgreſſion, and ſo have had Fellowſhip together in the Light of Righteouſneſs, and ſo Truth and Righteouſneſs was their Way, and Chriſt the Rock was their Foundation, which Foundation God hath laid, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11. and ſo they found Favour with the Lord, and ended their Days in Peace; but on the other Hand, this hath been the ſad unhappy State of Mankind, when they turned from God and Righteouſneſs, and Holineſs into Diſobedience, and ſo became wicked work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, filthy and corrupted with Sin and Uncleanneſs, and ſo the Devil through Deceit hath undone many to their Utter Ruin, and their Eternal Sorrow, and ſometimes perſwading the Creature one Way, and ſometimes another, ſometimes in profeſſion of Religion without the Life of Holineſs, which is an Abomination to the Lord; for unto the Wicked God ſaith, <hi>What haſt thou to do to declare my Statutes, or that thou ſhouldſt take my Covenant in thy Mouth?</hi> Pſal. 50.16. And ſo let all repent and turn to the Lord, that you may be ſaved; for the Truth is revealed that hath a long time been hid with the Lord even the ſame unchangeable immortal Seed, <hi>CHRIST,</hi> that bruiſeth the Serpent's Head; and though many are ſo vail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with Darkneſs, as to deny his working <hi>Inwardly;</hi> and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the holy one, yet he is come contrary to their Expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and therefore they receive him not: So the Way of God is not to be known in man's Way, nor yet in man's Time, nor in man's Will, but as man obeyes God and is ſubject to him, ſo he comes to know his Way. And ſo all People conſider theſe things whileſt you have time, and be warned to come out of Ignorance, and become ſenſible that you may underſtand; for God never forſakes any People without a juſt Cauſe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore lay it to Heart, and ponder this in your ſecret Meditations, and as your wiſe men tell you Revelation is ceaſt, let them
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53475:13"/>tell you, when? where? to whom? and for what cauſe? did God ever caſt off any People, when they were obedient to him? Nay, he never forſakes People till they forſake him, therefore the Cauſe is in man, and God is clear: So the Lord in his Mercy in theſe latter Days hath opened his Truth, and hath brought us into the Way of Life, wherein we ſee how the Apoſtacy came in, and in all Ages, and under every Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, the Cauſe was in men, becauſe they rebelled, and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from God; but now there are many ſo bewildred in their Minds, having loſt the good old Way, are perſwaded the Cauſe is in God, and that he will not work by his Spirit now, as he did in Days paſt, and ſo being deceived do not truly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to come out of Sin all their Life time, but imagine that God will accept of them in their Sins, and yet are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that they ſhall inherit Heaven, when this Life ſhall be at an End, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.5. whereas the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>The Heaven and the Earth that now is, are kept in ſtore reſerved unto Fire againſt this Day of Judgment and Perdition of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NGODLY MEN,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.7. ſo you may read your Portion here, if you turn not to God that you may be cleanled, where all your falſe Joyes and Pleaſures will come to an End, <hi>Amos</hi> 8.10. and everlaſting Sorrow will overtake you. And farther, as you deny the Working of the Spirit, and rebel againſt it, you are one with the old Backſliders, even from the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; for that was the chief Cauſe that God brought Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction upon the old World, becauſe they <hi>rebelled againſt his holy Spirit;</hi> for, after they departed from the Lord, yet his good Spirit did ſtrive with them, till at length the Lord was grieved, and ſaid, <hi>My Spirit ſhall not alwayes ſtrive with Man, &amp;c.</hi> Gen. 6.3. ſo the Day of their Viſitation paſſed away, and they were overthrown with the Flood, <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.23. ſo you may read and apply this to your ſelves; for you dare not ſay, but the Lord by his Spirit hath &amp; doth ſtrive with you (as in the dayes of <hi>Noah</hi>) who is reproving you in your hearts for your Prophaneneſs and Idolatry; therefore, while you have Time put into your Hands, Repent, and obey the Good Spirit of the Lord God, leſt God ceaſe ſtriving with you, and ſo you be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53475:14"/>by his Almighty Power, who is a terrible God againſt all Unrighteouſneſs: but all the holy People of God, before the Flood, were guided by his holy Spirit, which was a true Guide, and a ſure Leader from the Beginning; and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Truth was the Guide of all the choſen People of God after the Flood, even <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and that ſuſtained them in all their Travails, and was with them, as you may read at large in <hi>Gen.</hi> 12, &amp; 48. And this was the Foundation of all the Holy Men in all Ages and Generations. And when <hi>Iſrael</hi> at any time rebelled againſt the Spirit of God, which he gave them to inſtruct them, (read <hi>Neh.</hi> 9. through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out) then the Lord turned againſt them, and afflicted them, and cauſed them to be carryed away out of their own Land. Therefore the Spirit was and is the true Guide, and the true Fountain of Life, of Living Refreſhment and Heavenly Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, which gives true Wiſdom and a heavenly Mind, which when people forſook, and rebelled againſt it, then Ignorance abounded: And ſo you that rebel againſt God, who is a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, are you not one with <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Apoſtacy, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding your Profeſſion, againſt whom the Prophet teſtified, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>My People have committed two horrible Evils; the one, they have forſaken the Lord, the Fountain of Living Waters; and have hewen out to themſelves broken Ciſterns, that will hold no Water,</hi> Jer. 2.13. And is not this your State and Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this day? Are you not digging Wells of your own, and hewing out to your ſelves Ciſterns, and when all is done, it retains nothing pure, nothing holy, nothing clean, no living Water, nothing from Heaven, but all is corruptible, all filthy, all ſinful? Oh that your Eyes were opened to ſee theſe things! how ye are erred from the Life and Power, from the Living Fountain, with the old backſliding <hi>Jews</hi> and dark bewildered <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who in old time loſt the Light of the Sun of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs: but theſe things have happened through groſs Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes; as for inſtance, The general Belief hath been and is amongſt the outſide Profeſſors of Jeſus Chriſt, confeſſing only and believing, <hi>that Chriſt dyed without the Gates of</hi> Jeruſalem, though it is true; and ſo in a general ſenſe ſaying, <hi>We believe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53475:14"/>in God and in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> and ſo come no farther to any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Belief and Knowledge of him, as did the true <hi>Chriſtians, Rom.</hi> 8. from Verſ. 1. to 17. now here lies the Miſtake, and here many comfort themſelves, becauſe they confeſs to his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance in the World ſixteen hundred Years ſince, but this a man or woman may do and yet they may periſh; for to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs Chriſt and live in the Luſt of Uncleanneſs, is but to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment their Sorrow. becauſe there is a living Witneſs in them which they rebel againſt, and pierce, and ſo cauſe his Wounds to bleed afreſh, and put him to an open Shame, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.8. And notwithſtanding they may uſe Meats and Drinks, and have reſpect to Days and Times, Moneths and Years, yet all will paſs away, and periſh with the uſing, and the ground of the Separation from God may remain, and ſo you may eat and drink Damnation to your ſelves at unawares; for he that eats and drinks unworthily, is guilty of the Body and Blood of the Lord, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.27. therefore be warned whileſt you have time, and conſider theſe things whileſt your Day laſteth, that you may come to God (out of Sin and Death) by Chriſt Jeſus, who is come to deſtroy Sin in the Fleſh (mark that, in the Fleſh) this is a nearer Knowledge of him, then to confeſs him only as he dyed without the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> who is glorified with the Glory he had with the Father before the World was, and fills Heaven and Earth; neither is there any Creature that is not manifeſt in his Sight, but all things are naked and open to the Eye of him with whom we have to do, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.13. Therefore take beed to your Way, and mind that pure Eye, even the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Light within you, which is a ſure Word of Prophecy, to which ye do well if ye take heed, as unto a Light ſhining in a dark Place, till the Day dawn and the Day Star ariſe in your Hearts, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. And this is the true ſaving Faith, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Knowledge. to believe in your Hearts the Lord Jeſus, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.30, 31. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.8. And whatſoever Way or Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip there is, or may be this Day, or whatſoever Profeſſion or Confeſſion, otherwiſe then that which the ancient Apoſtles declared of, who were Eye-Witneſſes of his Majeſty, is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to Truth, and will not make the comers thereunto Perfect,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53475:15"/>who preacht from a certain Divine, yet Intelligible Principle revealed within them, which was the Seed Immortal, Incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, promiſed of God to deſtroy Sin &amp; bruiſe the Head of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and this Seed or Spirit of Life you muſt all come to know within you, to deſtroy Sin in Fleſh in your Mortal Bodies, and to quicken you from dead Works to ſerve the Living God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11. And this is the plain Truth unto you from the Spirit of the Lord, witneſſed by the Scriptures, as <hi>John</hi> well ſaid, when the ſpirit of Antichriſt began to work, and ſome were ſeduced by the Wicked One, ſaid he, <hi>Beloved, believe not every spirit, but try the spirits, whether they are of God; every spirit that confeſſeth that Chriſt is come in the Fleſh, is of God</hi> [mark] every ſpirit that confeſſeth Chriſt come in the Fleſh,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3.</note> who came to ſave his People from their Sin, and to deſtroy the Works of the Devil, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.2. for the Devil had wrought in the Fleſh of Mankind the Works of Darkneſs, Corruption, Uncleanneſs, and all manner of Fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs, in which he rules and Reigns over the Children of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, in that State and Nature which he hath begotten them into, and ſuch were thoſe ſometimes that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture mentions, who were by Nature Children of Wrath, even as others, but God, who is rich in Mercy, and abundant in Loving-kindneſs, cauſed his Love to break forth in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, the Brightneſs of his Glory (<hi>Hebr.</hi> 1.1, 2, 3) and viſited thoſe that were dead in Sins and Treſpaſſes, and quickened them by the Spirit of his Son; and ſo they were made Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Life of Jeſus, who begat them again, and Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them from the Bonds of Death by his Blood. So here is the Way of Life, and Path of Eternal Reſt, Chriſt Jeſus, the Power of God, which deſtroyes the Devil and his Works, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.8. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.14. and this is the true Spirit this day, we know it to our Souls Satisfaction, that confeſs Chriſt come in the Fleſh; and this was the Advice of the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> to ſuch as did retain Chriſt, the Power &amp; Wiſdom of God, which taught them all things, and inſtructed them in the things of God, and in the weighty Matters pertaining to Eternal Life; <hi>Little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I write theſe things concerning thoſe that ſeduce
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53475:15"/>you; but the Anointing that you have received of him, abideth in you; and you have no need that any man teach you,</hi> 1 John 2.27. and this was at that time when the Devil went about to deceive the Churches; for ſaid <hi>Peter, Your Adverſary the Devil goes about like a Roaring Lyon, ſeeking whom be may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</hi> And again, ſaith John, <hi>It is the Laſt Time, in which you have heard, that Antichriſt ſhould come; for even now there are many Antichriſts,</hi> 1 John 2.18. and <hi>Every spirit that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth not that Chriſt is come in the Fleſh, is not of God, but is a Deceiver; and this is that spirit of Antichriſt which ye have heard of ſhould come, and even now is already come into the World.</hi> 1 John 4.3. And this hath been and is to this day the loſs of many, in that they profeſs Chriſt Jeſus only outwardly come, and not try the ſpirits, that they may know Chriſt alſo inwardly, by his Spirit, Power and Wiſdom, crucifying the fleſhly Deſires, Affections and Luſts, that he alone may reign and rule: And this is the true Guide, Leader and Teacher of all the Children of the Lord in every Age and Generation, who is given for a Leader, even Chriſt Jeſus, the Light of the World, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.4. and ſuch as are not taught of him, they are not the Children of the Lord, but Children of him that hath ſtoln their Hearts from God, and leads them into For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulneſs concerning the weighty things, wherein conſiſts their eternal Peace; and ſo multitudes are deceived, and are Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers in the Darkneſs of the palpable Night, wherein the Thief hath robbed, ſtoln and deprived Thouſands of their. Right; for Man was not created for Deſtruction, but to inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit Life Eternal; and our God creates none to be deſtroyed, but that all ſhould be ſaved, and come to the Knowledge of his Truth, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. And therefore, if any periſh, its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they yield themſelves to the Wicked One to work Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, which is the Cauſe of Man's Miſery: And I certainly know, That no Man or Woman can have Peace with God, but as they come to witneſs in themſelves Reconciliation by Chriſt Jeſus, which can never be until they obey him; for this I find by good Experience, <hi>That Tribulation and Anguiſh is upon every Soul of man that doth Evil, to the</hi> Jew <hi>firſt, and alſo
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53475:16"/>to the</hi> Gentile, Rom. 2.9. <hi>both Profeſſors and Prophane,</hi> and notwithſtanding the Height of Profeſſion, where Chriſt Jeſus is not become the Head, or where that which is contrary to his bleſſed will is not yet put under his Feet in every particular, there is Condemnation and Terror within, &amp; ſecret Fears and Doubtfulneſs, which many Times cauſeth Torment, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4 18. And ſo in the Bowels of tender Love to all the Sons and Daughters of Men, is my Heart opened to declare the Truth, as it is in Jeſus, who is the true Foundation and Rock of Ages, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4. And for lack of the true and ſaving Knowledge of him, many have wandered in great Fear, and many to this Day wander from the Knowledge of him, and ſome whole Hearts (by the Nearneſs of God unto them) are tendered in Secret, and mourn in Secret, and are broken in Heart, in the Conſideration of their Conditions, whoſe Sins are laid before them by the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50 8. and know no Way to eſcape the Indignaion of Almighty God, but lye down in Fear and riſe up in Sorrow, thoſe are they whoſe ſecret Cry is to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known God, whom yet they are not come to know; but here is a Travail inwardly to enjoy the Redeemer, and here the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible, immortal God hath reached forth his ſpiritual Power, and ſome have come to a Deſire after the Lord, from a real Senſe of an inward Breathing after him, and yet have come ſhort of the thing they deſired in the Day of the Tenderneſs of their Hearts; for the Deſire begotten inwardly, it muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly be ſatisfied, and all outward things, as Ordinances and outward Obſervations cannot ſatisfie the Soul, and herein ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in this Day have come to a loſs, and have ſtumbled at the Foundation that God hath laid, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6, 7, 8. and ſo have over-run themſelves, and the tender Breathings of their Souls come to be ſtopt, and ſo comes up Hardneſs of Heart again, though the Pretence be never ſo fair, and here many ſtand in their Imaginations, fighting againſt the Appearance of God, and ſo many that might have been ſerviceable for God's Cauſe in their Day and time, and Witneſſes (in the Life of Jeſus) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Works of Darkneſs, are now become Enemies to the Lord that firſt begot them into Tenderneſs, in Days that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:53475:16"/>are gone and paſt; and this is the very Way, in which many Thouſands in this Nation have loſt themſelves, but a Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant there are that have obeyed the Heavenly Voice of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, that firſt touched their Hearts, and opened their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, whoſe Souls have continually mourned after him Day and Night, when Sorrow overtook us, and Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation was heard within our Dwellings, till we were ſenſible of the Way that leads to God's Kingdom, and then it was the true Deſire of our Souls to obey him, and follow him in the Way of his Judgement, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.20, 21. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.27. &amp; 4.4. and now he is become our Leader, who is the true Satisfier of the Soul, even Jeſus Chriſt (unto whom every one muſt give an Account) who is the firſt and the laſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.6. &amp; 22.13. the Beginning of the Creation of God, who hath all Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in Heaven and in Earth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18. and is near to all, who is that Grace of God, that bringeth Salvation unto man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 13. and theſe that obey him and hear him, who is the Beloved of the Father, according to his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.5. they are the true Church, the true Body, Chriſt Jeſus being Head, ruling by his bleſſed Power and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in every Member, and this Spirit and Power redeems the Church, and raiſes it up from the Grave, and ſuch come to know the Reſurrection of the Body, and the Paſſage from Death to Life, who obey Chriſt and know his Power in their Hearts to quicken and make alive; and ſo t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is mortal puts on Immortality, and this corruptible puts on Incorruption, and ſo Death is ſwallowed up in Victory, <hi>Iſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ah</hi> 25.8. And this is a holy Church redeemed to God, whole Light is God's Glory, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.23. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.19. and thoſe that are come to this Spirit and Power that overcomes the Devil, are true Witneſſes for the Lord, in this Age and Day, who are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from Death and Darkneſs, into Life and Light; and this is the Lamb's Wife which is eſpouſed unto him, betrothed in Loving Kindneſs, and confeſſeth him, and is not aſhamed of his Name before Men, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.32. and ſuch as have the Spirit they are the Children of God, but if any man have not the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pirit of Chriſt he is none of is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9. and theſe that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:53475:17"/>are obedient to the Spirit of Chriſt within them, they are a Living People, and are ſpiritually minded, waiting for the Promiſe of God to be ſealed up in Covenant with the Lord, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.22. And ſo they come to be a Habitation for God through the Spirit, that firſt cleanſeth and prepareth the Heart for God, and ſo it comes to be ſanctified through the Spirit by believing in the Truth, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13. And all other People that are gathered outwardly, without the Spirit, and Life and Power of God, that deſtroyes the Devill and his Works, are dead to God, and are yet in the Grave of Tranſgreſſion, and are in danger of falling into the deep pit of Miſery, where their Worm dieth not, neither is their Fire quenched, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.24. and ſuch are Hypocrites deceiving themſelves and others, and painted with an outſide, having the Sheeps clothing, but In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly are ravening Wolves: And ſuch as have not the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit for their Guide, run when God ſends them not, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie when the Lord ſpeaks not to them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.8, 9. as they in old Time that rebelled againſt the Spirit, and caſt the Word of God behind their Backs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.24. and ſuch are blind Watchmen, who are in the dark Profeſſion, over whom the Sun is gone down, <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.6. and Darkneſs is to them who have not a Viſion, <hi>Michah</hi> 3.5, 6, 7. but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny any ſuch Thing as Viſion and Revelation, and ſo are Night-Workers, not knowing whether their Work will ſtand in God's Day, or not; and ſuch were the blind Watchmen in the Dayes of old, when God did ariſe, and by his Word and Power in the Hearts of a People, moved the Inner man, and raiſed De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires after himſelf, but the Watchmen of the Night (ſaid the Church <hi>they found me and wounded me,</hi> Cant. 5.7. and here is the Time of trying the falſe Prophets; then ſayes the travailing Soul, <hi>I am troubled inwardly, and cannot be ſatisfied with all, my outſide Profeſſion, nothing will ſatisfie me till I come to enjoy the Beloved of my Soul, who is heavenly, and was ſent to ſave me from my Sins; Watchman canſt thou tell me where I may find him?</hi> But ſaith the blind Watchman, <hi>Revelation is ceaſt, no inward immediate Working of the Spirit now.</hi> And here many have been (and are) wounded to this Day; and this is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:53475:17"/>Teſtimony whereby you may know the true Prophet from the falſe; for the true Prophet comes in the Name of the Lord, ſtanding in God's Counſel, turning People to God, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Turn from Tranſgreſſion, and obey Chriſt Jeſus the true Light, that you may be made free,</hi> and ſaith the true Meſſenger, <hi>wait for the Son from Heaven,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.9, 10. And ſo many have obeyed this Glorious Goſpel, the Light whereof ſhines inwardly, and the Beloved is found that we ſought for amongſt the blind Watchmen, where we found him not; but it was but a little whil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, I was gone from the Night Watchmen, and I found him whom my Soul loveth, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.4. This alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, the falſe Prophet he comes with a Lye, preaching no Freedom from Sin, no Revelation, the Light within not the Way, not directing to the Heavenly Witneſs, which is able to ſave Eternally from Death and Miſery, but daubs up with untempered Morter: <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.10, 11. and ſows Pillows under the Arm holes of People crying, Peace, Peace, when there is none, healing the wound deceitfully, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.14. And ſo are Paſtors that deſtroy and ſcatter the Sheep of God's Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.1. but God will require his Flock at their Hands, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.10. and We will be unto them forever, who are found in the Way of the old rebellious amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> and profeſt Chriſtians, who tranſgreſs againſt the God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> whoſe Portion was with the Unbelievers and Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites where is Weeping and Gnaſhing of Teeth. And in the Riſe of the falſe Church, who went a whoring from Jeſus Chriſt, it was ſignified by the Spirit concerning her Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>I will caſt her into a Bed of Torment, and they that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Adultery with her, into great Tribulation,</hi> Rev. 2.22. And ſo all People conſider theſe Things, and come to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of the Son of God, which gives Life and Dominion over Hell and Death, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.54, 55, 56 which is the Good Old Way, the Path of the Righteous, and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Children of the Light of Jeſus Chriſt; and ſo all will know the Lord and be ſaved; for without this, Man is beneath the Beaſt of the Field; for when he was made Ruler over the Creation, he knew Dominion, and Power, and Wiſdom from
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:53475:18"/>on high, and was in the Image of God over the Creation of Beaſts, Fowls, Fiſhes and the Earth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26. but when he tranſgreſt againſt God, he loſt his Righteous Life, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Dominion, and fell under the Creation; and ſo <hi>the Ox knows his Owner, and the Aſs his Maſter's Crib, but</hi> Iſrael <hi>knows not his God,</hi> Iſa. 1.3. Jer. 8.7. now until this loſt Eſtate be reſtored to man again, and the Cauſe removed, which is Sin, Man remains in the Loſs, without God in the World, and there is no Way to come to that State again, but by Chriſt Jeſus, who is the Door the true Entrance, who ſaith, <hi>No Man knoweth the Son, but the Father, neither know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth any Man the Father, but the Son, and he to whom the Son will reveal him,</hi> Mat. 11.27. and this is the ſtanding Rule, which is unchangeable, and is from Everlaſting to Eve laſting, though it's vilified and lightly eſteemed of amongſt many, yet unto us he is the chiefeſt of Ten Thouſands, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.10. who hath redeemed us unto God out of our Sins, and waſhed us from our Filthineſs in his own Blood, to him be Glory for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evermore, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. And this is the ſure Rock, upon which God is building his Spiritual Houſe his Church, <hi>againſt which the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail,</hi> Mat. 16.18. And all that think of an Inheritance in Heaven, though they dye in their Sins, are in a great Miſtake; <hi>for no unclean thing ſhall enter,</hi> Epheſ. 5.3, 4 5, 6. And if any think of being cleanſed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this Life, and ſo made fit hereafter, this alſo will fail and come to an End; for <hi>after Death there is no Redemption, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie therefore your members whileſt you are upon the Earth</hi> Col. 3.5. for conſider the Rich Man who dyed, and lift up his Eyes in Hell, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.23. and cryed for Help from poor <hi>Lazarus,</hi> ver. 24. but all was in vain, there was no Remedy, nor Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption for him who had ſpent his Days in Pleaſure, and Van<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty upon the Earth, not ſo much as a little Water to cool his Tongue, when he was tormented in the Flame: And alſo you may read concerning his five Brethren, that he had left behind in his Father's Houſe, who were in the ſame Danger to be tormented with him, and therefore deſired they might be warned by poor <hi>Lazarus, leſt,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>they alſo come to this
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:53475:18"/>Place of Torment,</hi> Luke 16.28. So all you that are lofty and wanton upon the Earth, conſider your latter End, who ſpend your precions Time to the Fleſh, in the Luſt of Uncleanneſs, and nouriſh your Hearts, as in a Day of Slaughter, <hi>James</hi> 5.5. O remember the Day wherein the Holy Pure God will plead with you for all your Abominations, and for your Secret Sins, that you have committed againſt the God of Heaven, and how you make merry over the VVitneſs, that brings Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation upon you becauſe of your Sins, and even torments the VVorker of Iniquity in ſecret, this is the Faithful and True VVitneſs, even Jeſus the True Meſſenger, who brings G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidings to the impriſoned Soul, that's like to periſh in Iniquity, and this is he that was crucified in the Fleſh, but quickned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in the Spirit, by which Spirit he preached to the Spirits in priſon 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18, 19. And it may be thus men may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel agai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt him, and not turn at his Reproofs, but ſpiritually may crucifie him to themſelves, as ſome did in Days paſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.8. but it would have been much better that they had never had a Being; for when God ſhall call them to an Account for the Deeds done in the Body, then ſhall they cry to the Mountains, <hi>fall upon us, and to the Hills, cover or hide us from the Face of him that ſits upon the Throne, and from the Wrath of the Lamb,</hi> Rev. 6.15, 16, 17. <hi>for the Hour of his Judgment is come; and who ſhall be able to ſtand?</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore return unto him betimes before it be too late, that you may be reconciled to the Father, and ſo the Lord will return unto you; in his Love, and in his Tender Mercy will he viſit you, as you yield unto him in your Hearts; for ſuch as obey him this Day, do certainly injoy his Peace, and in his Name is their Safety, which is his Power, by which their Souls are kept from the ſpiritual Enemy, and therefore, O Land of my Nativity! hear the Word of the Lord God of Heaven, which VVord is near unto all the Inhabitants thereof, from one End unto another, that the Land may be cleanſed, and enjoy h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r Sabbaths, leſt Afflictions and great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orrow come in like a flood upon the inhabitants, from the Great God, whoſe Righteous
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:53475:19"/>Soul is grieved becauſe of the Abominations that are within thy Borders, who by his ſearching, living Power that is Eternal, over all (Death and Hell) is ſearching from one End to the other to bring Mankind into his Light and Life, to worſhip him in his Spirit and Truth, who is the bleſſed Creator of all, the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and the End, to whom be Glory forever, Amen.</p>
            <p>THE Righteous God, whoſe Power is great, and who is wonderful in Counſel, and excellent in working, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 28.29. hath in theſe laſt Days appeared inviſibly in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Parts of Mankind, to place his Name and his pure Fear in the Hearts of his People, according to his ancient Promiſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.16. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33. and to write his Law in the Hearts of his Children, who are truly turned unto him; and amongſt the many Witneſſes, the Lord who is rich in his Love unto Mankind, not willing that any ſhould periſh, he viſited me, who was a Wanderer in Deſolation from Year to Year, ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Way of the Redeemed of the Lord, and a Cry in ſecret was begotten in my Heart after God, who in his own time did hear, and Anſwer my Earneſt Deſire; and I well remember the Days of my tender Years, when I was very young, there was an Innocent Breathing within me after the Thing that is Good, and I ſaw Sin in its Conception, but knew not that which gave me the Knowledge of it; and Swearing I ſaw to be a great Evil in them that were addicted thereunto, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Nineth and Tenth Year of my Age, I was in a good Meaſure reſtrained from Evil, according to the Knowledge I then had, but afterwards when Years did encreaſe, I well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member my great Loſs; for evil Deſires did ſpring up within me, and by the ſubtil one I was betrayed, and led into divers Pleaſures, and Vanities of this Wicked World, and into many Evils which did diſpleaſe the Lord, and ſo the Tender Deſires which were after Righteouſneſs were ſlain, and then great Darkneſs and Sorrow did overtake me, and ſo into a ſpiritual Captivity from the Light that did ſhine within me in my ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:53475:19"/>Years, and ſo for many Years walkt in the Crooked By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paths of Darkneſs and Ignorance, in Diſobedience, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Knowledge of the true God, in which time I was a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to the Wicked One, and ſo are all that obey him, be they high or low, rich or poor; and after ſome Years I began to conſider my Condition, and ſomething within me bringing to Remembrance what I had done, and laying before me the Danger that attends the wicked, and in this time a Travail was begotten within me to ſeek the Lord, and repent of my Sins, and from Day to Day under the Indignation of the Lord which was revealed againſt me becauſe of Sin; and here was a Travail through much Fear and Doubtfulneſs what would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of my Soul if God ſhould cut off my Life, and indeed I could read <hi>Adam</hi>'s Condition, when he was afraid of the Lord and hid himſelf, becauſe he was naked; and in the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> I then was, and ſo loſt in the Fall, and as God behold me in that woful State,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.15.</note> ſubject to Bondage for Fear of Death, at laſt he opened unto my Soul the way of Life, howbeit Sorrow overtook me, and much Bowed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>downneſs did compaſs me about, and then the Enemy of my Soul wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d have taken away my Life, but the ſecret inviſible Arm of God's Power did uphold me, though I knew it not; ſo I ſay, God is the Saviour of all men, <hi>eſpecially of them that believe</hi> 1 Tim. 1.10. And as Tenderneſs was begotten in my Heart, ſo my Sins became a Burden too heavy for me to bear And this Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony I give in the Name of the Lord, that whoſoever feels the Weight of their Sins, it's by the working of God's Heavenly Power, begetting Tenderneſs in their Hearts though they know it not: And ſo none can come to God but by this Way, as our Lord ſaid, <hi>None can come unto me, except the Father that has ſent me draw him,</hi> John 6.44. And ſo my Heart was bowed before the Lord, and an Inward Deſire begotten, that none could ſatisfie but him alone: And I ſaw the Ways of Man in his corrupt Nature, were not thoſe which lead to God's Kingdom, and from Profeſſor to Prophane, all were gone aſtray, then my Cry was the more earneſt to the unknown God, and none amongſt my Worldly Relations, and Neighbours could tell me the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:53475:20"/>Way of my Soul's Beloved, till at laſt the Power of the Lord o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened my Underſtanding, and as I retired my mind inwardly in the Heavenly Light, I was made more and more ſenſible of the Operation of his bleſſed Spirit, which gave me Dominion over one Sin, and here was the Beginning of the Work of God in my Soul, and then I had a little Hope, of overcoming, and a little Faith to believe I ſhould be ſaved. So this is the Seed of God's Kingdom, which is immortal, compared to a little Leaven <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>d in three Meaſures of Meal, until the whole be lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened, which Seed is the Foundation which God hath laid, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11. for Man and Woman to build upon. And when all my Hope was loſt of getting out of that fallen State, and when I could not believe that I ſhould be ſaved, if I died in Sin, ſo that this Cry was within me, <hi>My Bones are dryed, my Hope is loſt, I am cut off for my Part,</hi> Ezek. 37.11. then did the Lord remember me, and manifeſted a Saviour in an accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Time, and as my Mind was inclined towards the inviſible Power that opened my Underſtanding. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.13, 14. ſo the Sins of Youth I overcame, and this is the Light of the Glory of God, that ſhined in my dark Heart, before I knew what it was; and ſo it is certain the Light ſhineth in Darkneſs, but the Darkneſs comprehendeth it not, <hi>John</hi> 1.5. and then I came to know God's Salvation near me, according to his Promiſe, <hi>Iſa</hi> 51.5. and ſo I ſaw the Days I had ſpent in Vanity, and began to redeem the Time, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.15, 16. and alſo how youthful Luſts and Pleaſures came over me in the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and how I was betrayed from my Innocent State, in the Days of my Childhood; ſo now I know this is the Spirit of Promiſe, that brings all Things to my Remembrance, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.26. and ſo my Soul by the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt was redeemed from dead Works, and out of the dark Ways of ſin and Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, into the Light of Righteouſneſs, to ſerve the living and true God; and this I affirm is the Spirit of Truth, that firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinceth the Conſcience of ſin, and then as it is obeyed, it lead<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> out of ſin, and roots out the Worker of Iniquity, and ſets up Righteouſneſs and Holineſs in the Heart, and this is the true Teacher, that comes to do the works that none other can do,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:53475:20"/>and ſuch as declare that which he hath done for their Souls, they are the true Meſſengers, as it is written, <hi>How beautiful upon the Mountains are the Feet of them that bring Glad-tidings, and publiſh Peace, bringing Glad-ridings of good Things,</hi> Rom. 10.15. and ſuch as are come unto this true Teacher (and abide with him) are happy forever; and as my Soul lamented in Days paſt for a Saviour, and languiſhed for lack of Spiritual Comfort, now I am ſatisfied fully, in that I feel a VVitneſs in my ſelf, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.10. which bears witneſs that my Soul is redeemed; and this was before me for ſome Years, to give a Teſtimony of theſe Things which God hath done for me, in reſtoring me to my Habitation, Everlaſting Praiſes be given to his Name forevermore. And as Man that is loſt in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> as he obeys the Heavenly and Spiritual <hi>Adam,</hi> Chriſt Jeſus, who never fell, ſo he comes to God again, and is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored into Life and a holy Liberty, vvith the Sons of God. And novv my Soul is made a VVitneſs for Jeſus Chriſt, that God ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h raiſed him from the Dead, vvho hath quickned me that was dead in Sins and Treſpaſſes, 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 15.45. And this is the Myſtery of Godlineſs, hid from the wiſe and prudent, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed unto Babes and Sucklings, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.21. And this Everlaſting Power that is now revealed, is that which will overcome, even unto the End, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21. and his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is everlaſting, and ſhall root out and deſtroy the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Wicked One; <hi>for he ſhall reign whoſe Right it a,</hi> Rev. 11.15. And now all you that have Deſires after the Lord, and are not come to the Knowledge of him, conſider theſe Things, and ſingly read theſe Line, that the ſaving Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God you may come unto, and then the Burden of Sin, an the heavy Weight will be taken away from your Souls, and then Life and Immortal Glory will be your Portion forever; for great, yea, unſpeakable is God's Love to his People, who are ſaved by him, and Infinite are his Mercies to he Souls of his Children; and though there be many miſerable Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that ſay, <hi>Revelation is ceaſt,</hi> ſo much as to ſay, <hi>The Way of God's Heavenly Mercies to the Souls of Men; is ſhu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> up,</hi> but bleſſed be the Lord, there are many Witneſſes this Day, unto
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:53475:21"/>whoſe mourning Souls God hath opened the Way of his Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Mercies, and they are come to the Faithful and True VVitneſs, even Jeſus the Mediator, and he openeth and none can ſhut, and ſhuts and none can open: And my Soul is made willing to invite all to come; for <hi>the Spirit ſaith come, and the Bride ſaith come, and let him that is a thirſt come and drink of the Water of Life freely,</hi> Rev. 22.17. that all may be ſaved from the VVrath to come, which will be heavy upon thoſe of this Generation, who ſleight the Day of their Viſitation; and therefore you that are come to ſeel your Sins to be your Burden, look not out for a Saviour, but wait for the Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Chriſt within, and you will find him to your great Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, and Everlaſting Comfort, and in your Age and Generation you will come to be VVitneſſes for God, and his Preſence you will come to know, in which is Life, and at his Right Hand are Pleaſures for evermore. And this is the Joy of my Soul, now God hath made me ſenſible of his VVay, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to do his VVill; and I know that ſuch as do not his VVill will be found on the left Hand amongſt the Hypocrites, and ſuch as are without God, unto whom it will be ſaid, <hi>depart ye curſed into Everlaſting Fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels,</hi> Mat. 7.23. Mat. 24.41. And then I well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, when this VVay of Life, firſt I came to knovv, and when I was ſeparated from my former Acquaintances, &amp; could not go with them into the ſame kind of Riot as before, they then turned againſt me, and I became a By wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d unto my Neighbours, and as the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>They think it ſtrange be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you go not with them to the ſame kind of Riot, ſpeaking e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil of you,</hi> 1 pet. 4.4. and ſo our Lord foretold of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e things, who ſaid, <hi>They ſhall caſt you out of their Company, and your Names ſhall be caſt out, as evil, for the Kingdom of God Sake; and when men ſhall perſecute you, and ſpeak all manner of Evil faſly for my Name Sake, rejoyce in that Day; for great is your Reward, liſt up your Heads, and be glad; for your Redemption draweth night,</hi> Luke 21.28. And this was that which did up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold me in that Day, even my Redeemer drawing nigh. And, now I have written concerning my Coming forth out of my
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:53475:21"/>Sins, and from the Wayes and Worſhips of the VVorld, who are not in the Spirit and in the Truth, and therefore will come to an End, and the true VVorſhip which is in the Spirit, and in the Truth, will be eſtabliſhed; for God who is ſtrong in Judgment, will raiſe up his own Tabernacle, <hi>Amos</hi> 9.11. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.16. and the Time is come wherein the Lord will work, and wo unto ſuch as endeavour to hinder his VVork, which is a righteous VVork, and will ſtand, when the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Sin ſhall end with Everlaſting Puniſhment; for it is Righteouſneſs. that will remain when God ſhall judge the VVorld, and ſearch out every ſecret VVork that hath been wrought in Darkneſs, yea, <hi>when Inquiſition ſhall be made for the Thoughts of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo all that read underſtand, and turn unto the Lord; for he is certainly riſen in great Power, yea <hi>he hath taken unto him his great Power, and is come to reign,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.25. for he hath ſeen the great Backſlidings of the Sons of Men and the Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that hath vailed the Creation, and the Death that hath reigned over Mankind; and he is come to take away the Vail that the Enemy of Mankind hath ſpread over the Nations, and to deſtroy the Face of the Covering caſt over all People, that Death may be ſwallowed up in Victory, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.54, 55 And the Holy, Pure God, whole Dominion is an Ancient Dominion, and his Heavenly Glorious Kingdom is from Everlaſting to Everlaſting, before the Devil and Death's Kingdom, Rule and Government was, he hath beheld the Sad Eſtate of the Sons of Men &amp; hath ſent forth a Saviour, who is mighty, the ſame that in Dayes paſt was mighty in word and Deed, before God and all the People, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.19. and the ſame Saviour, even Jeſus, which is Chriſt the Lord, hath redeemed and ſaved a People from their Sins, <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.21. who is able to bring forth all the diſtreſſed amongſt the People, whoſe inward Cry is to the unknown God, as mine was, who hath delivered my Soul from Death, who is my Shepherd, Biſhop and Teacher, in whom dwelleth all Fullneſs, who laid down his Life for his Sheep, whoſe precious Blood hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed us, whom my Soul hath Cauſe to extol and praiſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:53475:22"/>Night and Day, who is my Strength and Defence againſt all the Aſſaults of my Soul's Enemy, to whom ſaith my Soul, be Glory Everlaſting, and Praiſes for ever rendered, who is over all Bleſſed forever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this Work was begun in my Soul and my Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding opened to ſee the ſad and woful State of Mankind, being fallen into the State of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> in the Separation from God, and Chriſt Jeſus, my Heart was filled with Sorrow, and a Zeal for the Name of the Lord God did livingly ſpring in my Heart, and a Neceſſity was laid upon me to warn my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to turn unto the Lord; and the Lord ſhewed me the ſad and woful State of many whoſe Iniquities are even come to the full, and I warned them in the Name of the Lord in their publick Aſſembli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to turn from the Evil of their wayes, and now it lives in my Heart afreſh, to warn them by writing alſo, in the Holy Fear and Awe of the God of Heaven and Earth, in the deep Conſideration of their ſad Eſtate.</p>
            <p>And now my Neighbours, this is unto you in Bowels of tender Love, whoſe, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l deſireth your Everlaſting Good, that you may conſider your Wayes, and turn unto the Lord; for he is merciful, ſlow to anger, and of great Kindneſs, that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly you may be ſenſible of the Power of Jeſus Chriſt whoſe Heavenly Light ſhews you your Sins; for great are your Abominations which grieves the Lord God, and the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding thereof from Day to Day. How doth Drunkenneſs abound amongſt you, and Pride, and Vain Glory, and Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Lying from Day to Day abound, within the Borders of the Place of my Nativity? for whoſe Sakes my Heart hath often been bowed down before the Lord, that the Dayes of Sin and Iniquity may come to an End. Now Friends and Neighbours, there is no Way for you to eſcape the Indigrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lord, but by Repentance, and therefore repent ſpeedily, and forſake your Sins in this Day wherein the Lord hath viſited you with his Day Spring from on high, and that is the true Light that ſheweth unto you your Thoughts, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves you in Secret for Lying, Swearing and Drunkenneſs,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:53475:22"/>and all manner of Uncleanneſs; and that is the Day Spring from on high, revealed from God to lead out of Sin, and to ſave from Tranſgreſſion, and this is the Grace of God which the Apoſtle ſpake of which hath appeared unto all men, which is the true Teacher, and Leader out of Sin, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11. into Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines; and this will ſearch your Hearts, as you wait for it; for how have you been ſaying from Time to Time? <hi>At what Time ſoever a Sinner doth repent him from the Bottom of his Heart; God will blot out all his Tranſgreſſions out of his Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance,</hi> and do not many take Liberty to ſin becauſe of this, but as the Promiſe of Forgiveneſs upon Repentance, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.21, 22. commends the Mercy of God, that none might deſpair, yet the Lord will ſurely plead with all, that are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous and Continuers in Sin, read (your Portion) <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.20. therefore all both old and young, remember Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance from the Bottom of the Heart; for that you muſt all come to witneſs, if you be made clean, ſo that God may receive you. And indeed that is a Thing of great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment; but that is the Thing moſt wanting amongſt men; for there are Profeſſions enough, but I ſee but few that are come to the Cleanſing of the inſide, or inward Waſhing, but as the <hi>Phariſees, who made clean the outſide of the Cup or Platter, but the inſide was unclean,</hi> Luke 11.39 So there are many outſide Profeſſors of God and Chriſt, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their Sins, and Repentance, as they ſay, from the Bottom of the Heart, but the Cauſe remains, the Bottom is ſtill cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, and therefore that you may come to the Bottom that is the Deſire of my Soul, and the End of writing unto you; for you can never come to the Bottom, till you come to the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Truth, the Heavenly Light that lets you ſee the Bottom of your Hearts, and ſearcheth out the moſt hidden Things; for <hi>the Heart of Man is deceitful, and none can ſearch it but the Lord,</hi> Jer. 17.10. and the Lord knows it, and tries the Heart, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſearcheth the innermoſt Parts.</p>
            <p>And this is the Subſtance that is come, that ſearcheth the Heart and declares unto man his Thoughts, <hi>Ames</hi> 4.13. and as you obey him who is near you, even the Spirit of Truth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:53475:23"/>you will come to witneſs the Work you are a talking of, a Death to Sin, and a New Birth unto Righteouſneſs; for Chriſt Jeſus is manifeſt to take away Sin, renew Man and Woman again to God: And ſuch as come to witneſs Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance from the Bottom of the Heart, are the only People of God, who are come to the Foundation and Rock which is laid in the Bottom of the Heart that is cleanſed; for ſuch as are cleanſed to build upon. So this is the Truth, and is no Lye, and is a ſure Teacher, which is in Heaven, and not only ſo, but in the Earth alſo, by his Spirit and Power redeeming, and bringing up out of Captivity his Heritage, that mourned unto him, <hi>Jer.</hi> 12.11. being in Deſolation, and all falſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verings that ſerve for a Cloak for your Sins, as a bare Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and yet remain the ſame as before, will be too narrow to hide you from the Wrath of God, which is like to break forth upon you, except you repent. And therefore my Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Neighbours, I cannot but deal plainly with you to declare in Plainneſs the Thing that is upon me from the Lord; for I truly deſire your Everlaſting Good. And now you that are young, and think you have much Time to ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd, take heed to your ſelves, and remember the Lord before whom you muſt appear, that it may be well with you; for the Lord viſited me amongſt you in the Dayes of my Youth, not that I was better then others, but God who is rich in Mercy, heard the inward Cry of my Soul, and granted me Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance unto Life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.12. and that which I was ſaved by that declare I unto you, to be the only and alone Saviour, and there is not another, that can ſave from Sin but Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 4.29, 42. neither is there any Way to come to God but by him, <hi>John.</hi> 14.6 and there is no way to come to him but as you turn to his Light in your Conſciences, <hi>that lighteth every man that cometh into the World,</hi> John 1.9. So all repent and live; for Wo will overtake all the wicked, and great Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs will come upon them from the Lord; for the Day is dawned wherein he hath begun his Work, which he will car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on by his mighty Power; and it is in vain for any to gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay the Lord; and all falſe Profeſſions the Lord will bring
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:53475:23"/>down, and ſet up his Ancient ſtanding Rule over all, yea, the Standard of his Power, over the Devil, and all God's Enemies; for the Year of his Redeemed is come, and the Day of Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is in his Heart, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.4. who hath ſuffered, and hath been ſlain from the Foundation of the World, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.8. by the Wicked amongſt Men, and in many Ages and Generations he appeared ſpiritually, and by his mighty Power began to reform the Nations, but People dealt deceitfully with him, and caſt his Word behind their back, <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.26. and in this dark Night of Apoſtacy he hath greatly ſuffered with his Heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, which hath been in the Wildernſs, and in the Streets of that great City, which ſpiritually is called <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt</hi> where the Witneſſes have propheſied in Sack cloth and Aſhes, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.3. but now the appointed Time is come, wherein the Lord hath prevailed over him that hath darkned, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolated the People, and hath taken to him his great Power and is conquering, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.10. and in this his Day, he will cut his Work ſhort in Righteouſneſs; for a ſhort Work will the Lord make in the Earth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.28. and all Foundations of every Profeſſion are clearly ſeen in the Light of the Lamb. &amp; all whoſe Vine, is the Vine of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and Grapes, Grapes of <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> will be ſhaken as a Fig Tree that caſteth her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely Figs when ſhe is ſhaken with a mighty Wind, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.13. yea the Harveſt of the Earth will be reaped, and caſt into the Wine preſs of the Wrath of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.19. And he that People ſin againſt, whoſe Way you err and ſtray from, and whom you pierce by Reaſon of your wicked Works; I ſay, <hi>The Lamb that was ſlain, who liveth, and was dead, who hath all Power given unto him in Heaven and in Earth,</hi> Rev. 1.18. <hi>he treadeth the Wine preſs of the Wrath and Fierceneſs of the Almighty God,</hi> whom all Rebellious Chriſtians have forſaken, therefore will he bring Judgment into Victory, that Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs may run down as a mighty Stream; and happy, and bleſſed will all ſuch be that return unto him in their Hearts, who is come near to execute true. Juſtice and Judgment in the Earth, who is the Covenant of the People, the <hi>Gentiles</hi> Light, and <hi>Iſrael's</hi> Glory. I ſay, ſuch will ſee his Goodneſs, and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:53475:24"/>they only will be received into the Father's Kingdom being freed from the great Puniſhment due becauſe of Sin. And ſo my Country men, Repentance unto Life, yea, a Forſaking of your Sins, that will cauſe the Lord to turn from his Fierce Anger that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s like to break forth like Fire againſt you, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe will make up the Breach, and therefore, O my Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Place, I cannot but lament thee, becauſe I ſee the great A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations that are committed within thee, and not in thee only, but in the Places adjacent, but chiefly I am concerned for you who are my Acquaintances, that if by any means I might provoke you to fear the Lord, and conſider your latter End; for in the Way you are in which is ſinful, you will never find peace with the Lord; for the End is Sorrow, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is Death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. but if you forſake the Evil, and love Righteouſneſs, you will come into Life, and live for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever with the Lord; and that is the Travail I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>el within me concerning you, that you may walk in the Light, and come to a Holy Righteous Converſation, that you may have Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with us. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.3. and have Right to call God your Father, that you may be begotten of him, and ſo love one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other with a true Love in Righteouſneſs, and ſo come to know the Spirit of adoption, which is the Spirit of his Son, who breaks down the middle Wall, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.14. and blots out the Hand-writing of Ordinances that is contrary to us, and takes it out of the Way, nailling it to his Croſs, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.14. and ſo you will come into Covenant with God, in the Light of Jeſus, which Light leads to God's Kingdom, and conducts out of all the barren Wilderneſſes, &amp; Deſolations of the firſt <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> into a ſure Way, and Place of Defence in the ſecond <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> where is Safety, and a Place of Reſt, as he ſaid, <hi>Come unto me all ye that are weary and heavy laden: and you ſhall find Reſt to your Souls,</hi> Mat. 11.26. and ſo you will know the Truth, and the Truth ſhall make you free, <hi>John</hi> 8.32. and you will come to the general Aſſembly, and Church of the firſt born written in Heaven, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.32. and to have Right to the precious Promiſes of God, and to the Tree of Life; but while you continue in Rebellion againſt God, you have no
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:53475:24"/>Part nor Lot, or Inheritance amongſt the Living; for Sin is the Hindrance of the Promiſes and Bleſſings of God unto the Soul, whatever you may promiſe your ſelves, and think to inherit if you dye in Sin, nay; for man comes ſhort of all ſpiritual Bleſſings, notwithſtanding all his Wiſdom, Parts and Abilities; for God hath placed Cherubims, and a Flaming-Sword, which turns every Way to keep the Way of the Tree of Life, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.24. and here man is defeated, notwithſtanding all his fair out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Shew or Pretence of Religion; for without Obedience to Chriſt, he is undone and loſt, though he may retain the Name Chriſtian, and as ſome in Dayes paſt, who had a Name to live, and were dead, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.1. and ſtood as though they were Rich, and had need of nothing, but knew not that they were Poor, Blind, Wretched, Naked and Miſerable, and ſo were without the City, New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> without a Part or Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in the Kingdom of God; though they had a Name, yet were dead to God, in the Profeſſion only without the Life, and ſo were threatned, as ſaid the Spirit, <hi>I will kill her Children with Death, and all the Churches ſhall know that I am the Lord, that ſearcheth the Heart, and trieth the Reins, and give to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one according as his Work ſhall be,</hi> Rev. 2.23. &amp; 3.17. And ſo dear People, come into the Light of Chriſt that is within you, before your Glaſs be run, that you may find a Place of Repentance, leſt the Dayes come over you when Repentance ſhall be hid from your Eyes, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 13.14. and ſo with <hi>Eſau</hi> ſeek the Bleſſing when it is too late, and a Place of Repentance with Tears, and could not find it, therefore while it is called to day, if you will hear his Voice, harden not your Hearts, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.7, 8. but draw near unto the Lord, and he will draw nigh unto you, and gather you unto himſelf, and you ſhall no more wander without the Knowledge of him, but the gathering Arm of God's Power will keep you from the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of your Immortal Souls, who is a Thief, and a Lyar from the Beginning, and a Murderer, who abode not in the Truth, <hi>John</hi> 8.44. and ſo you will be with the Redeemed of the Lord, whoſe Hearts are in Covenant with him, who are come to the Blood of Sprinkling, that ſpeaks better Things then
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:53475:25"/>that of <hi>Abel, Heb.</hi> 12.24. and ſo you will know a ſure Teacher, even Jeſus Chriſt, who is a Prieſt forever, after the Order of <hi>Melchizedek,</hi> whoſe Miniſtration is Life, who hath the Words of Eternal Life, <hi>John</hi> 6.48. And this Teacher cannot be removed into a Corner, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.20. who is the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der gathering Shepherd, and careful over-ſeeing Biſhop, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.25. which leads by the Springs of Living Water, and guides to the Fountain of Life, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.17. and here you will find Power and Wiſdom, Strength and all things needful; for God hath laid Help on one that is mighty, which is the mighty Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer and Reconciler of Man to God; and this is that ſecret Joy that ſpringeth up in my Soul from day to day, feeling the holy Power of the Lamb of God, that taketh away the Sins of the World, who hath delivered my Soul, and now he doth miniſter Joy and Comfort to my inner Man, in the Senſe whereof my Soul ſaith, <hi>Come all ye ſcattered ones, who are yet wandring as Sheep having no Shephe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, come to the Fold of Reſt; Oh! let your Hearts be bowed down and tendred before the Lord, who is riſen in this the Day of his Power, and hath made a little Remnant willing to follow him, whoſe Eye is render, and ſeeth, every ſecret thing, and beholdeth the Breathings of the Souls of the Children of Men, who have Deſires after him; and all you that mourn in ſecret, cleave unto him who hath toucht your hearts, and go not forth, but be retired in your Minds, and he will make way for you through all, and ſo Fear not them that can kill the Body, but fear him that hath Power to caſt both Body and Soul into Hell</hi> (Luke 12.5.) <hi>and ſo ſuch as will obtain Life, let them take up the Croſs, and deſpiſe the Shame</hi> (Hebr. 12.2.) <hi>and turn your Backs upon all the World's Pleaſures &amp; Delights, and follow Chriſt in the Regeneration, and be of</hi> Moſes<hi>'s Mind, who eſteemed it greater Riches to ſuffer Perſecution with the People of God, then to injoy the Pleaſure of Sin for a ſeaſon,</hi> Hebr. 11.24, 25. <hi>for the Wo reacheth forever to Man and Woman in the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, if they Repent not; and that State is attended with the Wrath of God, and the Lord's Diſpleaſure, which is a ſufficient Diſcouragement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo read theſe Lines in Coolneſs of ſpirit, and in a ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:53475:25"/>weighty ſenſe of your preſent Conditions, &amp; then you will receive Benefit thereby, and the End will be anſwered for which this is written; ſo being clear in my Conſcience, in that I have done as I was drawn in Spirit by the Lord God of Heaven and Earth, to declare unto the World in general and to ſome more particularly, that which was opened to my Underſtanding, to warn People concerned herein to turn unto the Lord, I ſhall leave the Iſſue of all unto him who knoweth all Hearts, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into my Reſt in that Meaſure of Grace given me of God, where with my Brethren and Siſters, who are redeemed out of the Sins of the World, I ſhall give Glory to him that ſits upon the Throne, and to the Lamb for evermore, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.13. which was, and is, and is to come, who is our God, our King and Law-giver, before whom all muſt appear, who is God over all bleſſed forever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Richard Samble.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:53475:26"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>GOD, who is Everlaſting in his Being, and Mighty over all in his Power, rewarding ſuch as obey him with Life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, Joy, Peace and everlaſting Comfort; and alſo reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Wicked with Puniſhment and Sorrow for evermore. When firſt he created Man and Woman, he created them in his own I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, in Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs; but ſoon after the Creation, the Devil prevailed over them, and corrupted their Hearts, and ſo they loſt the pure Preſence of the Lord; and then, as the World came to be peopled, ſo did Wickedneſs abound in the Earth, although the Lord did ſtrive with them by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that they might return and live, but they continued in the Rebellion againſt the Lord, and then the Lord ſaid, <hi>My Spirit ſhall not alwayes ſtrive with man &amp;c.</hi> Gen. <hi>6.3.</hi>—and ſo God brought the Flood upon them, and their Blood was upon their own Heads: And after the Flood, though great was the Deliverance of <hi>Noah</hi> and his Family, in that great Deluge wherein many Thouſands were overthrown, yet one of the Sons of <hi>Noah</hi> became a Wicked Man, and the Curſe came over him, <hi>Gen. 9.25.</hi> and as the World became peopled again, ſo did Wickedneſs encreaſe, and people grew up in Ignorance, without the Knowledge of the true God, in Rebellion againſt the Lord; and then God appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> and commanded him to forſake his Father's Houſe, and his Kindred, <hi>Gen. 12.1.</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> believed and obeyed God, and was faithful in all things before him, with whom the Lord made a Covenant, and the Promiſe of Life was unto his Seed, wherein all the Nations of the Earth ſhould be bleſſed; and the Promiſe of God unto <hi>Abraham</hi> was, <hi>That his Seed ſhould inherit the Land wherein he was a Stranger;</hi> ſo God bleſſed <hi>Abraham,</hi> and multiplied his Seed as the Stars of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and they encreaſed unto a multitude in the Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and the <hi>Egyptians</hi> intreated them evilly, and afflicted them Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Hundred Years, <hi>Gen. 15.13.</hi> and afterwards God remembred
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:53475:26"/>his Covenant made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and raiſed up a Prophet, to wit, <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was faithful in all God's Houſe, and by mighty Signs and Yokens of his Judgments upon <hi>Egypt,</hi> God brought them forth by a mighty Hand and an out ſtretched Arm, and preſerved them by the Way from the Expectation of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and kept them in the Red Sea from being overtaken with the <hi>Egyptians;</hi> and God did this for them, to the end <hi>they might be unto him a Choſen People, to ſet forth his Praiſes to the Ends of the Earth:</hi> But ſoon after this great Deliverance, when they came into the Wilderneſs, the Devil by his Subtilty turned their Hearts from the Lord, and ſo Iniquity was found within their Camp, and Murmurings amongſt the People, and ſo God was diſpleaſed, and cut down their choſen men who luſted by the way, and raiſed up another Generation amongſt them, and they enter'd the Land, and God gave them his Law and his Statutes, that they might be a People known to the Lord, in obeying him forever; but ſoon after they came into that Inheritance, the Devil wrought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to turn their Hearts from the Lord, and they followed the Wayes of the <hi>Heathen</hi> whom God caſt out before them, and then the Lord was grieved with them, and gave them into the Hands of their Enemies, who ruled over them, until they ſhould remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Lord, againſt whom they had ſinned; and when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred the Lord, he ſent Deliverance unto them, which brought them again to their Land: And ſo all may read who have <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, what the Cauſe is this day, why people do not injoy the Bleſſings of God unto their Souls, its certainly becauſe they are in the Tranſgreſſion: But God will remember ſuch, though they may be in ſpiritual Captivity, that deſire after him, and forſake their Sins, which is the Cauſe of their Souls Captivity; for when the Heart ſhall return unto the Lord, he will take away the Vails, and give an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding of the thing that's Heavenly: So <hi>Iſrael</hi> dealt treachtrouſly with the Lord from time to time; but the Lord often times, when they cryed unto him, raiſed up faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Meſſengers, which declared unto them the Way of the Lord; and <hi>David,</hi> whom God choſe, with whom he confirmed his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe before made unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>David ſhall not want a Man to ſit upon his Throne forever;</hi> but this People, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:53475:27"/>
               <hi>Iſrael,</hi> were Corrupters, and followed their own Inventions, and rebelled againſt the Spirit of God, and ſlew the Prophets of the Lord, which he ſent unto them: And ſo the Time came when God according to his Promiſe, ſent his Son, the Seed, wherein the Bleſſing conſiſts, in which all the Nations of the Earth ſhall be bleſſed, which is to gather into one all things in Chriſt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Heaven or in Earth, <hi>Epheſ. 1.10.</hi> But the <hi>Jews,</hi> though they were the Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> outwardly, yet did not know this ſpiritual Seed, Chriſt, but roſe againſt him, and put him to Death, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>beit God raiſed him from the Dead by his Glorious Power, and received him again into his ancient Glory, that he had with him before the World began; but God turned his Hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe profeſſing Perſecutors, and the Time came over them that Diſtreſs and Sorrow compaſſed them in, and Affliction and Tribulations from day to day attended them, becauſe of that bloody Action, in Conſenting to the Death of Jeſus; and ſo God's Fury was poured forth upon them from time to time, until they were diſinherited and driven out of their Poſſeſſion, which if they had received him, and believed that it was he, Eternal Life and Glory would have been their Reward for evermore: And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this time, God, who is rich in Grace, after Chriſt Jeſus, the Son of his Love, was raiſed up from the Dead, began to appear in him, and to work by him inwardly in many, and raiſed up ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to bear witneſs of God, <hi>that he had raiſed up his Son from the Dead,</hi> whom he furniſhed with the Gift of Life, Power and Wiſdom, to declare unto the Sons of Men, <hi>That Jeſus was the Chriſt;</hi> and this was the Goſpel which before was preached unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> unto whoſe Seed the Promiſe was forever, which Seed is Chriſt; and many Thouſands by this glorious Goſpel were ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered to God, and a glorious Way they were brought into, and alſo into the injoyment of the ſure Mercies of <hi>David,</hi> Iſa. <hi>55.3. never to be forſaken, nor yet to want a Man to execute Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> (in their Behalf) <hi>in Truth and Righteouſneſs:</hi> But here comes the Miſery again, the Devil, who was ever an Enemy to God's Heritage under every Diſpenſation, he begins to work a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and to ſeduce the Minds of ſuch as profeſs Chriſt Jeſus, and then Wickedneſs again began to ſpring, and as Wickedneſs aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:53475:27"/>ſo people were darkened in their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding; and as the Wicked One prevailed, ſo people were corrupted; and this was the beginning of falling away again from God, after the Appearance of Jeſus Chriſt: And now, as the <hi>Jews</hi> and all Apoſtates in days paſt have rebelled againſt God, ſo have theſe called <hi>Chriſtians</hi> rebelled againſt Chriſt, and ſo Darkneſs and Ignorance came over thoſe called <hi>Chriſtians</hi> alſo, and the Devil hath ruled, and hath had Dominion, and then God, who firſt appeared to them in his Son Chriſt Jeſus, when they thus rebelled and grieved him, he with drew his Preſence from them, and ſo they have been a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring People from Generation to Generation; but God, who is E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting, though Man hath changed in his Mind, yet God is the ſame, and changeth not; and that Bleſſed Truth and Everlaſting Goſpel, which is not another, in theſe laſt dayes hath God revealed again, and its now profeſt, injoyed and preacht by the deſpiſed Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple called <hi>Quakers,</hi> whom God hath gathered by the Right Hand of his Righteouſneſs, to bear forth a Teſtimony for his Name, in this Generation, whom God will ſupport, uphold and ſtrengthen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Oppoſitions, that his ancient Truth may be proclaimed to the Ends of the Earth, that ſo ſuch as are afar off may be brought nigh to God, &amp; the Devil ſhall be defeated, whoſe Power of darkneſs hath reigned, and Chriſt Jeſus ſhall reign, whoſe Right it is, and he ſhall bring us into the Poſſeſſion of the ſpiritual <hi>Canaan,</hi> that Land of Eternal Reſt which remains for the People of God; and he will chain the Devil that has deceived the Nations, &amp; caſt him into the Bottomleſs Pit, and his holy People ſhall poſſeſs and inherit forever the bleſſed Kingdom; <hi>and the Wicked and Abominable, and Murderers and Adulterers, and all Lyars, ſhall have their Part in the Lake that burns with Fire and Brimſtone, which is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Death,</hi> Rev, <hi>21.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. S.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
